<root>
<page>006v</page>

<div>

<id>p006v_1</id>

<ab>The ardor of Paris laid Troy, where so much<lb/>
vitality could be found, to ashes.	<lb/>
Thus is many a good Spirit seduced in youth <lb/>
by this blind god of Desire remains only a spark,<lb/>
or drowns like a child before he knows of water.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p006v_2</id>

<ab>63. They judge like <i>Paris</i>, the most foolish of all.<lb/>
The Painters’ Marriage is often of this sort:<lb/>
beauty pleases their senses the most. <lb/>
Rather, pay attention, and be less hasty.<lb/>
Leave Bacchus’ son <i>Hymen</i> with the other Gods; <lb/>
Think, it will not be so quickly forbidden.<lb/>
To avoid Headaches it is good, they say,<lb/>
to breakfast early and to marry late.<lb/>
</ab> 

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>On the painter’s rash marriage.</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p006v_3</id>

<ab>64. To do things well–this cannot begin too early, <lb/>
and doing badly cannot be put off too long.<lb/>
If good comes without difficulties, <lb/>
then it is precious beyond all treasures; <lb/>
its most proper use is to combat sorrow. <lb/>
But there is no need to set a time:<lb/>
This can be found in <i>Piero Mexia’s</i> <lb/>
second Book, Chapter Thirteen. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>One cannot make a good marriage too early, or a bad one too late. <lb/>
Praise for a good marriage. 
</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p006v_4</id>

<ab>65. There it states that the girl must be <lb/>
about ten years younger than her Spouse, <lb/>
as the mellifluous Poet <i>Ariosto</i> <lb/>
also declares in his <i>Satires</i>;<lb/>
but our Painter (if no pressing matter troubles him) <lb/>
before he establishes himself well, <lb/>
should for love of Art, visit the Lands<lb/>
in every corner of the World.<lb/></ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>A Girl should be ten years younger than her Spouse at the Wedding.</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p006v_5</id>

<ab>66.  I would urge you wholeheartedly to travel, <lb/>
if I did not fear that you might begin to stray.<lb/>
For <i>Rome</i> is the city which, more than other places, <lb/>
is the destination of many Painters.<lb/>
It is the principal school of <i>Pictura</i>, <lb/>
but it is also above all the place<lb/>
where wastrels and prodigal Sons spend their fortunes;<lb/>
one shrinks from allowing one’s Child to go there.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>
Travel to Rome is discouraged, since there is much opportunity to spend money uselessly and nothing good to earn.</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p006v_6</id>
<ab>67. One also comes to know this from experience, <lb/>
since many come from there penniless.<lb/>
For it is a place where error is fed,<lb/>
indeed, a nest of treachery, where all evils<lb/>
that spread over the world today are hatched. <lb/>
So says <i>Petrarch</i>, and what he says further <lb/>
about it that is worse, too long to recount here, <lb/>
is difficult to refute from truth.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --> </ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p006v_7</id>
<ab>68. Yet one should fall in love with the Country’s charm,<lb/>
and <i>Italus’</i> people, descended from <i>Janus</i>, <lb/>
</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --> </ab>
</div>
</root>