<root>
<page>044r</page>

<div>

<id>p044r_1</id>

<ab>
19. To keep them from conflicting.<lb/>
For example, the lakes support many clear blues,<lb/>
and the smalts support white lakes; <lb/>
clear massicot can sit well next to green.<lb/>
Let ash-white can be shadowed with brownish yellow,<lb/>
purple, with blue or red, and, indeed, let the different<lb/>
half-tints be enhanced with clear ones.<lb/>
Here one must try a variety of ways. <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Observe colors in order to make reflections.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p044r_2</id>

<ab>
20. Sometimes large flat panels of cloth <lb/>
look beautiful worn by stately Men;<lb/>
sometimes one sees this also on the hoods of Monks.<lb/>
where two folds of fabric overlap <lb/>
one another, whether stretched or relaxed.<lb/>
Further, on occasion, do not exclude<lb/>
some modern costumes which are <lb/>
in use nowadays, or worn in the past. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Beautiful large panels of Silk, with here and there a gleaming fold, have a fine look, as do Monks’ hoods and modern clothes.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p044r_3</id>

<ab>
21. What further should I indicate to you?<lb/>
Where you should, with bold intelligence,<lb/>
lace up, slash, or loop edges, collars, slips, <lb/>
and hems hanging halfway to the knee?<lb/>
Make facings, trimmings, braids, and buttons,<lb/> 
tied up here, open there, over and under Clothes, <lb/>
chemises and laces; cloaks, veils, <lb/>
and a thousand elegant fabrications?<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Various particulars of clothes.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p044r_4</id>

<ab>
22. Test, seek, and invent, observe the work of others,<lb/>
pick up something as you design;<lb/>
temper, transform, seek to combine<lb/>
what you can bring to good form.<lb/>
Make this your goal. And, for good drapery,<lb/>
prepare your first layer well and add glazes,<lb/>
which will help it achieve a shining transparency,<lb/>
for making Velvets and beautiful Satins.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Enhancing them with glazes.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p044r_5</id>

<ab>
23. While you achieve elevation in Fabrics<lb/>
by highlighting all the folds, <lb/>
it is quite different with Velvets.<lb/>
Indeed, you make everything dark, and only<lb/>
make only smooth highlights on the edges of the folds.<lb/>
But as regards the coloring of any silk Satins, <lb/>
I can offer you no more bountiful Example<lb/>
Than life, which is the Master of every Painter.<lb/>
</ab>

<margin>right-middle</margin>Of Velvets and silk.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p044r_6</id>

<ab>
24. One sees various styles of Fabrics<lb/>
in the work of great Masters:<lb/>
<i>Raphael</i> of <i>Urbino</i> worked wonders here,<lb/>
and considered his folds after the proper custom.<lb/>
Some Figures are dressed quite simply, some richly;<lb/>
<i>Buonarotti</i> was even in his colors,<lb/>
But some that he made in stone<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Examples of Italian Fabrics. </ab>
</div>

</root>