<root>
<page>025r</page>

<div>

<id>p025r_1</id>

<ab>
to be the eyes; and that nowhere can<lb/>
love and doleful pain be better perceived.<lb/>
They are mirrors of the soul, messengers of the heart,<lb/>
Which there reveal affection and envy,<lb/>
steadfastness and passion, gentleness and delight.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>O<!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p025r_2</id>

<ab>
27. From these two lights which guide the body, <lb/>
sympathetic tears and streams of sorrow<lb/>
spread over the blooming fields of the cheeks, <lb/>
the heart releasing itself with bitter cries.<lb/>
It is remarkable when is released,<lb/>
where so great a reservoir of moisture resides <lb/>
and where it stays hidden, still and quiet, <lb/>
when one has a merry and cheerful heart.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p025r_3</id>

<ab>
28. Thus we understand how to depict a happy heart<lb/>
when that worry is banished:<lb/>
we ought to make the eyes half-closed<lb/>
and the mouth open, sweet, laughing, cheerful.<lb/>
And we need to bear in mind<lb/>
The Latin term <i>laetae</i> <i>frontis</i>, <lb/>
A happy forehead, which is smooth and simple<lb/>
and unencumbered with many wrinkles.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On depicting a happy mood.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p025r_4</id>

<ab>
29. We must pay attention, I say,<lb/>
to the brow (which the Pagans<lb/>
dedicated to <i>Genius</i>), according to some<lb/>
the Soul-revealer, and the Gaze of thought,<lb/>
the Book of the heart, to read and examine<lb/>
the human spirit. For wrinkles and grooves<lb/>
show there, that in us is hidden<lb/>
a gloomy spirit, oppressed, full of care.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On the brow, revealer of the Soul, and the Book of the heart.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p025r_5</id>

<ab>
30. Yes, the brow is like the Sky and weather,<lb/>
where sometimes great gloomy clouds blow over, <lb/>
so is the heart is burdened with worry and discontent;<lb/>
but all dark mists fall away, the Sky is restored<lb/>
by the comforting wind and morning sunbeams,<lb/>
clean, pure, azure, to refresh the spirit,<lb/>
and the Light of the Sun<lb/>
triumphs, like a Hero who has won the battle.<lb/>
The brow compared to the Sky.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The brow compared to the Sky.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p025r_6</id>

<ab>
31. The brow smooths out when worry takes flight, <lb/>
and the eyes joyfully clear up:<lb/>
for <i>Genius</i> is not good at deception,<lb/>
and Nature (they say) cannot lie:<lb/>
but those who exhibit a cheerful brow<lb/>
and have a heart full of angry blame,<lb/>
they are double-browed, and indeed are called <lb/>
the worst enemies, who look friendly.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Of the double-browed, and who are the worst enemies.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p025r_7</id>

<ab>
32.  Also observing the various raisings<lb/>
of the two eyebrows sheltering the eyes, <lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>On the eyebrows, where a person’s thoughts can be recognized.</ab>

</div>

</root>