<root>
<page>008r</page>

<div>
<id>p008r_1</id>

<ab>
80. I observed the unsettled <i>Arno</i> too, <lb/>
sometimes dry, sometimes overflowing its banks;<lb/>
but it cost <i>Hannibal</i> his eye,<lb/>
seemingly from revenge, since he had tormented<lb/>
the <i>Etruscan</i> Lands with war. <lb/>
I saw the water of <i>Trebbia</i>, <lb/>
where <i>Sempronius</i> repented, too late, of his pride, <lb/>
with great damage to the Roman army.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p008r_2</id>

<ab>
81. I have further sailed on two beautiful Rivers.<lb/>
There are no others like them <lb/>
For they are the most important to adorn <i>Europe</i>. <lb/>
The first is the <i>Danube</i>, called <i>Ister</i> <lb/>
in other regions, which (as some say)<lb/>
pours so powerfully into the <i>Black Sea</i> <lb/>
that the salt waves must part before him <lb/>
and let him sweeten the salt water for forty miles.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Herodotus in <i>Melpomene</i>, Book 4, considers the Danube the greatest of all rivers
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p008r_3</id>

<ab>
82. Next I consider the grand and useful River <i>Rhine</i>, <lb/>
graciously flowing through our Netherlands,<lb/>
the most worthy of praise; <lb/>
I have visited these Waters <lb/>
and many honorable Cities<lb/>
to understand, with better insight, the Art <lb/>
whom I now intend to depict <lb/>
with a pen, as I know her.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p008r_4</id>

<ab>
83. Since in my youth I covered so much ground<lb/>
to please her, for what it is worth,<lb/>
she must, in recompense,<lb/>
allow me to reveal her essential elements<lb/>
and various Laws and customs,<lb/>
to be of some service to the intention<lb/>
of Aspiring and eager Minds.<lb/>
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p008r_5</id>

<ab>
84. I hope to do this according to my ability, <lb/>
and not blindly, for in order to avoid mistakes <lb/>
I have suckled at various breasts, <lb/>
invented a little, and borrowed much <lb/>
from old as well as modern writers.<lb/>
For I notice that this usually the case:<lb/>
that even excellent Writers <lb/>
must have fished in other Ponds.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p008r_6</id>
<ab><margin>bottom</margin><b>End of the Exhortation.</b></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p008r_7</id>

<ab><b>
CHAPTER II: ON DRAWING, or THE ART OF DRAWING.<lb/>
The Second Chapter.</b></ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p008r_8</id>

<ab>1. One may call Drawing, or the exalted <lb/>
art of Drawing, the Father of painting;<sup><comment>1 Quoting Vasari I, 43.
Vasari calls drawing the father of architecture, sculpture and painting; as Miedema points out, VM extends the arts to seven.
Miedema 425.</comment></sup> <lb/>
and one can also praise it as the right path, </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Drawing, the father of good painting, or: drawing is the Body and painting is its Soul.
</ab>

</div>
</root>