<root>
<page>012v</page>

<div>

<id>p012v_1</id>


<ab>
and the other two legs must do the same.
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p012v_2</id>

<ab>
10. Such movement, running or walking.<lb/>
One sees people doing naturally,<lb/>
Whether in motion or standing still.<lb/>
If this is observed well in our profession<lb/>
So in children, men and women,<lb/>
Our labor shall be properly crowned;<lb/>
We must take care not to have the arm and leg<lb/>
Move forward on the same side of the figure.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
An action common in people and animals, walking or stepping forward.
</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p012v_3</id>

<ab>
11. But we need to consider an exchange;<lb/>
let the right arm come forward<lb/>
and the right leg hang back,<lb/>
and the left leg come forward while, conversely,<lb/>
the left arm goes back,<lb/>
always crosswise. Whether the figures are sitting<lb/>
or standing, the face must follow<lb/>
the arm which moves forward.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On employing a crosswise action, which masters from ancient and modern times have offered to us as examples.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p012v_4</id>

<ab>
12. Raphael of Urbino and Michaelangelo,<lb/>
have shown such postures
in their artistic work; the like<lb/>
can also be found in antiquity,<lb/>
in various figures, artfully carved;<lb/>
and in the beautiful city of <i>Florence</i><lb/>
is such charm to be noted <lb/>
in the well-sculpted work of Giovanni da Bologna.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p012v_5</id>


<ab>
13. In nature, one sees in standing poses<lb/>
that the head is generally turned in the same direction<lb/>
that the foot is pointed; and further, one notices<lb/>
that the body will always settle itself and move<lb/>
according to the turning of the head, which it supports.<lb/>
Yet this composition is praised more fully<lb/>
according to the rules of posture,<lb/>
if the head is turned in a different direction from the body.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On turning the head away from the direction of the body.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p012v_6</id>


<ab>
14. But/otherwise a weak poor quality will dissatisfy us;<lb/>
thus must one attempt in many ways<lb/>
to turn the head for the best composition,<lb/>
for such can wholly destroy or embellish<lb/>
the quality of the figure, in the eyes of the wise. <lb/>
But no turning the head is tolerated<lb/>
for sacred figures, which one tries one’s best<lb/>
to make prayerful and modest.<lb/>
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Sacred figures do not need much turning of the head.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p012v_7</id>


<ab>
15. Thus one shall not always be bound<lb/>
by the aforementioned <i>Pose</i><lb/>
but, as is found to be necessary,<lb/>
to vary it sometimes:<lb/>
for <i>Orpheus</i> changed his sweet-sounding harp<lb/>
and played with jarring chords<lb/>
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>One must strive in every way for correctness, and sometimes change things.</ab>

</div>
</root>