<root>
<page>031r</page>

<div>

<id>p031r_1</id>

<ab>
Poetry ought to study<lb/>
What color needs to be next to which, or not,<lb/>
such as blue with purple, and the purple with red,<lb/>
and with red the orange-yellow, <lb/>
then light yellow befriends green,<lb/>
and green wants to be with blue.<lb/>
And from ash-blue and yellow one mixes green. <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Painters learn from the Rainbow which colors go together.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p031r_2</id>

<ab>
24. In the same manner, using certain rules,<lb/>
those who go to work on damp plaster<lb/>
prepare their <i>tavolozze</i> or boards,<lb/>
and the Oil painters also use <lb/>
the same arrangement on their palettes<lb/>
white by one’s hand, then from each saturated color<lb/>
is mixed two or three lighter tones.<lb/>
These methods are ready and useful.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Those who work on damp plaster mix two or three lighter tones from each color, keeping the white next to the hand.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p031r_3</id>

<ab>
25. Indeed, the times Painters devote<lb/>
to mixing colors will only be time gained;<lb/>
there is no need to argue this point.<lb/>
But to continue with Radiance,<lb/>
such as moonlight, fire, lightning, candlelight, and forges: <lb/>
one ought to judge, in each particular case,<lb/>
how in lighting the surrounding area,<lb/>
one always creates the same type of radiance.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Mixing colors is never a waste of time, but is very beneficial.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>One must pay attention to colors and the appearances of all kinds of lights in order to distinguish among them.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p031r_4</id>

<ab>
26. The light of night–the Moon–shining <lb/>
on houses and Churches, above and below,<lb/>
will bestow a glimmer as pale as itself<lb/>
on everything it touches.<lb/>
Likewise the lightning, a harbinger<lb/>
of violent thunder, chases the darkness<lb/>
with a particularly blue fire<lb/>
and furthermore, reveals its Reflection fleetingly.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!--Nothing in margin--></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p031r_5</id>

<ab>
27. We find, as we read in <i>Pliny</i>,<lb/>
Art of Reflection also practiced in ancient times<lb/>
by <i>Antiphilus</i> who, being an expert,<lb/> 
painted a youth blowing on a fire <lb/>
with lively devotion to keep it burning;<lb/>
and because of this blowing, the glow revealed<lb/>
the interior of a very fine dwelling<lb/>
as well as the flickering on the blower’s face, skillfully done.  <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Example of someone blowing on a fire, done by the ancient Painter Antiphilus.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p031r_6</id>

<ab>
28. <i>Echion</i>, whom we discuss elsewhere,<lb/>
also wished to portray the Art of Reflection,<lb/>
having revealed through the spreading of light,<lb/>
a lovely young Bride going to bed,<lb/>
following behind an older Matron: <lb/>
to lighten the darkness,<lb/>
she carries a fiery burning Torch<lb/>
and proceeds with a modest bearing.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!--Nothing in margin--> </ab>
</div>

</root>