<root>
<page>052v</page>

<div>

<id>p052v_1</id>


<ab>
<b>XIV. Meaning of Colors, what can be signified by them.<lb/>
The fourteenth Chapter.</b>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>E<!--nothingin margin--></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p052v_2</id>

<ab>
1.  Because the Sun shows such a strong force<lb/>
that Moon, Stars and all earthly lights<lb/>
must yield before its extraordinary clarity,<lb/>
and because its rays resemble Gold,<lb/>
and Gold is the first among metals,<lb/>
we will organize our remarks<lb/>
distinctly so that first, very important,<lb/>
we propose that yellow represents Gold.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On Gold.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On the overpowering light of the Sun.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The Sun resembles Gold.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Gold considered as yellow.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p052v_3</id>

<ab>
2. Of all useful and praiseworthy colors,<lb/>
we begin with yellow, the most magnificent,<lb/>
since it represents the beautiful color of Gold.<lb/>
Yes, Gold, which feeds the ever hungrier<lb/>
senses of greedy men without satisfying them.<lb/>
this brilliance from the insides of the abyss,<lb/>
pulled from the belly of our Mother for us all,<lb/>
has always brought much harm in the world.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Through Gold, or for the sake of gold, many bad things have occurred.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p052v_4</id>

<ab>
3. For the unreasoning desire of the weak<lb/>
Is already wrong, and not due to Gold.<lb/>
<i>Cadmus</i>, the discoverer, was the first to acquire Gold.<lb/>
Two Kings of Colchis took the earth’s virginity,<lb/>
for the sake of Gold, in the region of <i>Samnium</i>;<lb/>
they worked to collect gold from the water <lb/>
with Sheepskins, from which <lb/>
the legend of the golden Fleece arose.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Salauces and Ebusopes.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>From which the legend of the Golden Fleece arose.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p052v_5</id>

<ab>
4. Yes, the Legend of the <i>Argonauts</i>, companions of <i>Jason</i>,<lb/>
which has traveled almost the entire world.<lb/>
It is stranger to read, than worthy of believing, <lb/>
How, to triumph without Hercules, <lb/>
they put a woman to work;<lb/>
but Gold, to recount the origin of its name,<lb/>
<i>Hippocrates</i> believed it came <lb/>
from <i>Aurora</i>, like saffron, and glowing.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Orpheus, Valerius Flaccus, and Apollonius have written about the journey of Golden Fleece.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Where Gold would have gotten its name</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p052v_6</id>

<ab>
5. Or, as <i>Isidorus</i> says, its name is derived <lb/>
from the Latin aura, which indicates <lb/>
a glow of clear appearance.<lb/>
Nor is <i>Gregorius</i> silent about <lb/>
its singular gleaming quality. <lb/>
And in general People always like to see,<lb/>
with awakened senses, what is<lb/>
pure, clear, and lustrous.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p052v_7</id>

<ab>
6. The clearest beauty is invisible<lb/>
Beauty, the gracious origin of all beauty, <lb/>
which is also compared to the Sun,<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

</root>