<root>
<page>002v</page>

<div>

<id>p002v_1</id>

<ab>but waste their time excessively: <lb/>
"They have too much of what I have too little,<lb/>
yet we actually have the same amount,"<lb/>
by which he apparently meant the time that he, active in many areas, <lb/>
tried to win with diligence, so that he was always short of time.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p002v_2</id>

<ab>16. There are certainly more of the time-poor sort,<lb/>
who want to split each interval into three,<lb/>
practicing making time out of no time.<lb/>
But one also finds those who always have a great deal of time,<lb/>
however recklessly they spend it;<lb/>
so they carelessly throw it away <lb/>
on Pots, Cups, Golfing and Ball-playing<lb/>
because they care nothing for its worth.<lb/>
</ab> 

<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>This was once portrayed ingeniously by Goltzius.</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p002v_3</id>

<ab>17. Nevertheless (alas) what shall we lack more, <lb/>
finally, than precious time, <lb/>
when we must leave this earthly nest?<lb/>
The present time is now at hand, <lb/>
but yesterday is forever past<lb/>
and tomorrow uncertain: no one can say<lb/>
he knows if he will reach tomorrow. <lb/>
In sum, time surpasses all riches.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>How precious time is.</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p002v_4</id>

<ab>18. But people find it less significant <lb/>
to while away time with song, lutes and harps,<lb/>
taking walks for the digestion, <lb/>
or what is called sharpening the senses,<lb/>
than to let go of gold or silver, <lb/>
which really are worth less than time <lb/>
and its favorable opportunity <lb/>
which, once it has once flown by, we can never get back.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Time and occasion, or the favorable point in time, once gone, can never be retrieved.</ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p002v_5/id></id>

<ab>19.  Thus the loss of time is a great damage,<lb/>
repaired with neither goods nor money.<lb/>
So, children, be more frugal with time than with gold<lb/>
and drive away laziness, which is <lb/>
the mother of all evil and the nurse of poverty;<lb/>
then further, every evil brings its own rod <lb/>
for just punishment, and is not afraid <lb/>
to strike at its instigator or master.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>
<lb/><lb/><lb/>
Idleness, the mother of all evil and the nurse of poverty.  
Every evil brings its own punishment.
 </ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p002v_6/id>
<ab>20. The drunkard falls in the muddy gutter <lb/>
And, being needy, must endure much discomfort. <lb/>
And what proceeds from drunkenness <lb/>
but all shameful and dreadful actions <lb/>
which are to be regretted in a sober condition; <lb/>
in particular the irreparable act of murder, <lb/>
when man's hands grip and break <lb/>
the work of God, which no one can repair. <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>There ought to be a Book as an introduction for young Painters, for learning to place a Figure with ease, and thus leading to greater perfection. </ab>
</div>

<div>

<id>p002v_7</id>
<ab>21.  See what this barley beer can cause;<lb/>
how often it reduces men to pigs <lb/>
</ab>

</div>
</root>