<root>
<page>034v</page>

<div>

<id>p034v_1</id>


<ab>
having eaten a moderate evening meal, <lb/>
restore and return to cheer with sweet sleep<lb/>
your weary memory and restless senses.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>In summer, one should rise and retire early, and listen to the singing of the Birds.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p034v_2</id>

<ab>
3. Come! Let us open the Gate early<lb/>
for some short time together, to lighten our spirits,<lb/>
and behold the beauty to be found outdoors.<lb/>
There the wild beaked Musicians are piping;<lb/>
there we should take note of many sights<lb/>
which will serve us in constructing Landscape<lb/>
on linen or planks of Norwegian hard oak.<lb/>
Come! you will (I hope) be grateful for the journey.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p034v_3</id>

<ab>
4. See, over there, the Bride of old <i>Tithonus</i>i>, <lb/>
rising from her saffron bed, <lb/>
who comes to announce the torch of day.<lb/>
And, bathed in the Ocean’s <i>Ghewat</i>i> <lb/>
four spotted horses rearing and panting,<lb/>
and see, the hem of blooming rose<lb/>
on these purple clouds, how lovely hangs<lb/>
the bright house of <i>Eurus</i>i>, to receive <i>Phoebus</i>.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Tithonus’ Bride is Aurora, the Dawn. “Ghewat” is a stream of water where animals drink.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Schillede is spotted or pied.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p034v_4</id>

<ab>
5. And look at what is painted up above,<lb/>
what greater beauty, what a variety of colors<lb/>
and so much blending! Aye, one could believe<lb/>
that molten Gold would gleam thus in a crucible,<lb/>
glittering like the Clouds spreading there!<lb/>
And the distant blue hills prepare<lb/>
to carry the banner of the new Sun,<lb/>
which comes rushing on its pebbled wheels.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Observing what happens at Dawn.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p034v_5</id>
<ab>
6.  Look! On the other side, Dawn<lb/>
has already covered the great heavenly vault<lb/>
with a fine azure drape; hidden beneath it, <lb/>
the Lamps, which tend the brightness at night;<lb/>
and the face of the day-bringer glows like fire,<lb/>
coming to bedew the tresses of <i>Tellus</i>i>,<lb/>
and has laid many drops on the grassy<lb/>
woven garment of this green world.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Tellus is the Earth: her Hair, the plants and grass, which are sprinkled with dew</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p034v_6</id>


<ab>
7. Look how the fiery yellow round ball<lb/>
of the Sun has already risen, as a surprise<lb/>
while we were standing facing elsewhere!<lb/>
Look yonder: the Hunters with their Dogs<lb/>
run through the dewy green fields.<lb/>
Indeed, look how this dew informs us,<lb/>
betraying their presence with <lb/>
the greener green of their footsteps.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Notice how one sees, looking against the Sun, the fields blue-green with dew; and one can recognize the tracks of Hunters or dogs who have run through there.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p034v_7</id>


<ab>
8. Observe how, in the distance, the Landscape <lb/>
takes on the appearance of the Sky, and seems to blend into it,<lb/>
immobile Mountains resemble moving clouds, <lb/>
and the pits and furrows that we see in the fields<lb/>
</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Let the distant Landscape vanish or sweetly merge into the sky.</ab>

</div>

</root>