<root>
<page>050v</page>

<div>

<id>p050v_1</id>


<ab>
Nonetheless, in that time the Colors kept<lb/>
their own purity, lacking none,<lb/>
while they could not be seen.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050v_2</id>

<ab>
4. To speak of this further: I believe<lb/>
that the colors, as we have always seen them,<lb/>
are all revealed by and have the nature of<lb/>
the four Elements, hard or soft,<lb/>
when the Sun shines on them, or where the light falls.<lb/>
However, one might well ask what is color itself, <lb/>
which, in its various manifestations,<lb/>
Is constituted from the four Elements.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Colors derive from the Elements.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050v_3</id>

<ab>
5. Color is, in itself, the external visibility<lb/>
of a body to which it belongs,<lb/>
while yet being the substance of light;<lb/>
because the troubling darkness, by its thickness, <lb/>
prevents the eye utterly from perceiving difference;<lb/>
while daylight in particular grants vision the gift <lb/>
of clearly distinguishing, without error,<lb/>
how each color is constituted.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>What color is.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Daylight is the most suitable for distinguishing Colors.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050v_4</id>

<ab>
6. The clarity of light, after Darkness disperses, <lb/>
brings out the beauty of Colors.<lb/>
Then, the powers and virtues of Colors are revealed,<lb/>
for there is nothing, no matter how unimportant,<lb/>
which does not have its color. And finally, in sum:<lb/>
nothing can exist without color,<lb/>
whatever its nature, even strange,<lb/>
and all colors are built on the foundation of the visible.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>No visible thing is without color.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050v_5</id>

<ab>
7. There are two sorts of color<lb/>
(according to the insight of <i>Pliny</i>)<lb/>
despite the number of pigments:<lb/>
that is, natural, and those made with art.<lb/>
The natural [ones] are named after the Countries <lb/>
where one can find them; reciting all these names<lb/>
would be easier to desire than to do,<lb/>
and the list would be far from complete.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>There are two kinds of Colors, natural and artificial.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050v_6</id>

<ab>
8. Color, the particular natural quality <lb/>
of all things, whether still or moving, <lb/>
is the topmost garment and outermost covering,<lb/>
whether it be single colored, mixed, or multicolored.<lb/>
Many things have the name of a color;<lb/>
they provoke and satisfy that hungry look<lb/>
of eyes which, in the World’s vast kitchen,<lb/>
ceaselessly long for their food: to see more<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>More on what Color is, and what it does.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050v_7</id>

<ab>
9. Color can reveal the differences among things,<lb/>
such as clearly distinguishing Gold from Bronze;<lb/>
Color makes persons bold or frightened,<lb/>
Color makes ugly or beautiful,<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

</root>