<root>
<page>032v</page>

<div>

<id>p032v_1</id>


<ab>
All this one sees well done, with a musician’s brilliance,<lb/>
by this Villager who was such an accomplished painter.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p032v_2</id>

<ab>
41. In sum, the height to which this Man has ascended<lb/>
in depicting Reflection with expert art,<lb/>
is not only renowned for his many Landscapes<lb/>
but even the gold-tester <i>Battus</i> will applaud:<lb/>
for in the Capital City I happened to see<lb/>
by chance some Passion nocturnes,<lb/>
where in the ground color of stone were numerous darks, <lb/>
and the rays of light were incised in gold. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>I saw these small pieces in Rome; they were painted on tablets of touchstone.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p032v_3</id>

<ab>
42. But why am I mentioning a foreigner?<lb/>
I ought to consider <i>Congiet</i>,<lb/>
Netherlandish-Italian Painter, <lb/>
all of whose colors submitted to him<lb/>
whenever he would set them to work.<lb/>
Indeed, not one dared to disobey his Laws,<lb/>
but had to do and become<lb/>
as his ideas commanded.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Congiet was also clever with fire and light</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p032v_4</id>

<ab>
43. And where the colors were at the limit<lb/>
and unable to fulfill his intention, <lb/>
he set out boldly with the son of <i>Iapetus</i><lb/>
to the chariot of the King of the Planets.<lb/>
So that his fire and his lights might live,<lb/>
he artfully employed gold<lb/>
to make his fires swell and glow<lb/>
and make his lights sparkle like stars.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Coignet made candlelight, which seems to burn, from raised gold bumps.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p032v_5</id>
<ab>
44. With colors he can marvelously burn<lb/>
the city of <i>Pluto</i>, or destroy <i>Troy</i>;<lb/>
he can have <i>Judith</i> displaying the head of <i>Holofernes</i> at night,<lb/>
with Torches, Brands and Lanterns in the street, <lb/> 
and in the background a gathering of people.<lb/>
He did this, for example, for the Lottery Prize,<lb/>
commissioned by the Regents of the Insane Asylum in Amsterdam,<lb/>
not to mention other pictures of his there.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Examples of some pieces by Congiet.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p032v_6</id>


<ab>
45. Then just as <i>Pictura</i> favors the <i>Batavians</i> <lb/>
as much as <i>Sicyonans</i> in former times,<lb/>
Nature came to the port of Haarlem <lb/>
to throw everything in her bosom and bestow it<lb/>
in the hearts of two of its residents.<lb/>
One is truly a Painter: One of his,<lb/>
in Amsterdam, is The Cave of <i>Plato</i>,<lb/>
in which the Art is extraordinary.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Another Example, of Plato’s Cave, by Cornelis Cornelisz. Van Haarlem, a piece in Amsterdam.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p032v_7</id>


<ab>
46. There one sees Reflections flashing everywhere<lb/>
as a group of prisoners, lying in the dark,<lb/>
seem to be battling, using Arguments,<lb/>
about shadows of Figures cast by the light of a Lamp,<lb/>
some, in freedom, see figures and shadows,<lb/>
</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

</root>