<root>
<page>005r</page>

<div>
<id>p005r_1</id>

<ab>of the troubled, foul waters of Lethe, <lb/>
from which no knowledge dreams. <lb/>
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005r_2</id>

<ab>45. Artists, Scholars, Monarchs and Commanders, <lb/>
in brief, have ascended to fame and esteem <lb/>
by suppressing laziness,<lb/>
and hard effort and glorious acts. <lb/>
We should not get far in the world <lb/>
without the sound practice of work, <lb/>
the fruits of which provide utility, repose and joy.<lb/>

</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
The utility of diligence and labor.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005r_3</id>

<ab>46. Hearing this, O Youths, follow the road<lb/>
of work as swiftly as possible, for the end is sweet.<lb/>
Paint, draw, scribble, freely blot any sheet<lb/>
of Paper as if it waits for it.  <lb/>
Steal arms, legs, bodies, hands, feet –<lb/>
nothing is forbidden here. Those who want to<lb/>
must play the role of Rapiamus well.<lb/>
Well-cooked turnips make good soup.<lb/>


</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005r_4</id>

<ab>47. Try to escape the Poetic art of Rhetoric,<lb/>
with its charming ways, however desirable and sweet.<lb/>
I myself have not done a great deal to avoid it,<lb/> 
but it has often deterred me <lb/>
from the path of Painting, which is to be feared.<lb/>	
It is indeed a lovely flower; if it bore fruit<lb/>
and provided flour ready for the Kitchen,<lb/>
then the urge to use it would come. <lb/>


 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Rhetoric, a lovely flower without fruit, is discouraged because of the jealousy of painting.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005r_5</id>

<ab>48. In the Workshop with other apprentices, <lb/>
honor a Contract never to quarrel; <lb/>
even if you are the best, help the worse ones<lb/>
maintain the tools in the Workshop.<lb/>
Pay attention to the Master’s Palette and Brushes, <lb/>
to cleaning and preparing canvases and panels, <lb/>
to grinding pigments finely, to keeping them clean,<lb/>
and not to temper ashes and smalts too much.<lb/>
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005r_6</id>

<ab>49.  Begin suckling at the pure breasts <lb/>
of the ingenious maiden who bears weapons<lb/>
and came from Jupiter 's brain, as the Poets say,<lb/>
then bow willingly to general opinion.<lb/>
In this regard, keep company with <i>Apelles</i>,<lb/> 
for you will often acquire something <lb/>
–when you lend a patient ear– <lb/>
which was unknown to you before.<lb/>

 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
One should also pay attention to the opinion of ordinary folk.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p005r_7</id>

<ab>50.  Do not bother with the Heralds of <i>Midas</i>,<lb/>
poor judgments which ring falsely, <lb/>
but guard yourself against the weakness of <i>Momus</i>.<lb/>	
Even if you think there are clear mistakes<lb/>
In the Master’s work, do not speak of it;<lb/>
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Do not bother with the bad judgment of the ignorant. <lb/>
Do not call anyone's attention to the errors of the Master.

</ab>

</div>
</root>