<root>
<page>037v</page>

<div>

<id>p037v_1</id>


<ab>
these are all matters of the spirit, and the spirit learns to make them.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p037v_2</id>

<ab>
38. One can make good use of different leaves,<lb/>
especially aflame with various colors:<lb/>
yellow, green oak-leaves, the pale leaf of willow stems.<lb/>
One should not finish Tree-tops  <lb/>
as entirely round, as if they were trimmed or combed,<lb/>
but display branches growing densely on all sides<lb/>
of the trunks, most substantial down below,<lb/>
but letting them thin out above.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Different leaves and colors of the Trees.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Not making the Treetops round.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p037v_3</id>

<ab>
39. One must also recognize typical Tree-trunks <lb/>
which are large underneath and slender as they rise upward;<lb/>
at times distinguish sparse white birches, <lb/>
Kapok and Linden, and apply yourself to<lb/>
the oak’s wrinkled bark and green cover,<lb/> 
and also the straight trunks, useful <lb/>
for tightening sails where the wind may heave;<lb/>
These are all dressed in their canopies of green.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Of trunks and branches.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p037v_4</id>

<ab>
40. To arrange the Trees well is beneficial,<lb/>
whether sparse shrubbery or a great Forest,<lb/>
some yellower, some greener. Make sure to show <lb/>
the undersides of some leaves, while not making<lb/>
leaves too small and delicate, to avoid a dry appearance.<lb/>
While painting foliage, try further<lb/>
to show how these sprigs expand erratically;<lb/>
some bend twisting upwards, others down.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>To construct Trees well.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p037v_5</id>
<ab>
41. It would be good if you acquaint yourself first<lb/>
with your story, from Scriptures or Poets as you please,<lb/>
to link your Landscape to it better.<lb/>
But above all, and never forget,<lb/>
to add Small Figures to large Trees.<lb/>
The little World you have made is ready to enter,<lb/>
there to mow, over there, to travel by wagon,<lb/>
elsewhere to fish, sail, fly and hunt.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>That it is good to know one’s History already.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Small Figures next to large Trees.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p037v_6</id>


<ab>
42. Here let Peasant Maidens loosen their hands<lb/>
from the Milk-springs along the verdant shore,<lb/>
there <i>Tityrus</i> with his Flute brings delight<lb/>
to Amaryllis, his most beloved of Women,<lb/>
sitting in repose under the Beech tree;<lb/>
and beguiles his herd with sweet sounds.<lb/>
Yes, fill your Country, City, and Water with activity;<lb/>
populate your Houses; place wanderers on your roads.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On the figures in the Landscape.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p037v_7</id>


<ab>
43. Here it is fitting to tell the story of <i>Ludius</i>,<lb/>
who lived in the age of Emperor <i>Augustus</i>,<lb/>
who first discovered how to paint well and artfully<lb/>
on the Walls, outdoors or in rooms,<lb/>
Farmhouses, Homesteads, Vineyards, roads,<lb/>
and thick Forests, elevated Hills, <lb/>
</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Here is the example of Ludius. Pliny Book 35, Chap. 10.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Read about this in his life.</ab></div>

</root>