<root>
<page>017v</page>

<div>

<id>p017v_1</id>


<ab>
27. Regarding their <i>Veil</i>, or explanations concerning it,<sup><comment>4 See Book II, 17-18. The “veil” is the threaded screen VM recommends as a grid for drawing.</comment></sup> <lb/> 
I will here be silent, and instead discuss<lb/> 
copious and simple Histories<lb/> 
so that each may choose<lb/> 
which one their feelings most incline to:<lb/> 
but many good Masters avoid<lb/> 
the principles of abundance or <i>Copia</i>,<lb/> 
and do well with simplicity.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On the Veil which I have discussed in the chapter on Drawing, on abundant and simple Histories.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p017v_2</id>

<ab>
28.  Such masters (so to speak)<lb/> 
do not imitate Procurers or Lawyers,<lb/> 
who employ many words in pleading [a case],<lb/> 
but copy great Majesties<lb/> 
and powerful Potentates,<lb/> 
who do not put forth much talk<lb/> 
but give their meaning verbally,<lb/> 
or with their pen, in few words.<lb/> 
</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Great masters do not create abundant histories, but resemble great Lords, who speak little yet keenly.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p017v_3</id>

<ab>
29. And such simple reasoning<lb/> 
earns them a greater reputation<lb/> 
than excessive babbling and prattling,<lb/> 
like empty vessels which make the most noise: <lb/> 
thus it seems that our great Masters learn<lb/> 
to turn towards plainness,<lb/> 
and how to give their objects <lb/> 
a beautiful bounty with few images.<lb/> 

</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p017v_4</id>

<ab>
30. And through that, great perfection is found<lb/> 
in their Figures, which move as if almost alive,<lb/> 
seemingly built on foundations<lb/> 
by poets who produced Comedy or Tragedy <lb/> 
to be performed with a few characters,<lb/> 
or they follow <i>Varro</i>, who did not seek<lb/> 
the great roar of many guests at the table<lb/> 
when he held festive banquets.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example of simple Histories, in Theater, or at Banquets.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p017v_5</id>


<ab>
31. But in order to delight, according to his plan,<lb/> 
he chose a select group of people<lb/> 
and invited them to his banquet,<lb/> 
nine or ten, so that no one would prevent <lb/> 
another from enjoying himself.<lb/> 
However, in a simple mode, it is not praiseworthy<lb/> 
To depict crude or trivial things,<lb/> 
Which bring no harmony to the eyes.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Crude things in simple histories are not to be praised.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p017v_6</id>


<ab>
32. As <i>Zephyr</i> comes to meet <i>Flora</i>,<lb/> 
where, in former times, they would kiss,<lb/> 
and the many-hued songsters greet <i>Aurora</i>,<lb/> 
Yea, there the new blossoms seek the light;<lb/> 
the honey-seekers, who long for sweetness,<lb/> 
cannot always rest on <i>Adonis</i>;<lb/> 
they do not want to miss <i>Crocus</i> and <i>Smilax</i>,<lb/> 
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Similarity between a painting and a flowery field, where the eyes are like bees, happy among a variety of different artful blossoms.</ab>

</div>

</root>