<root>
<page>048r</page>

<div>

<id>p048r_1</id>

<ab>
And this layer was a flesh tone.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048r_2</id>

<ab>
18. When dried, they could see their subjects<lb/>
clearly before their eyes, almost half-painted.<lb/>
Then, they put down the other layers<lb/>
in one sitting, with a singular effort and skill.<lb/>
They did not apply paint in very thick layers,<lb/>
but in a thin light, delicate manner, <lb/>
always brilliant and clean,<lb/>
by drawing fine white hairs, as in life.<lb/>

</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Bringing things together painstakingly, and then transferring them neatly, is advantageous in painting.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048r_3</id>

<ab>
19. O rare <i>Dürer</i>, Germany’s pride!<lb/>
At Frankfurt in the Monastery one can see<lb/>
This pure refinement, worthy of the name.<lb/>
Yes, <i>Bruegel</i> and <i>Lucas</i> too, all flourishing.<lb/>
One can justly write <i>Plus</i> <i>ultra</i> in the kingdom<lb/>
Of Painters, which, before them, was firmly enclosed<lb/>
Such that no one could easily follow,<lb/>
no more than Jan, the first of all.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Dürer’s work at Frankfurt as an example.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Bruegel, Lucas, and Jan van Eyck, examples of the practice of finishing cleanly in a single sitting.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048r_4</id>

<ab>
20. They were very attentive to this refinement,<lb/>
and placed their colors beautifully, neat and fresh.<lb/>
They did not load their panels as we do now, <lb/>
so that with eyes closed, one could touch<lb/>
and perceive the work almost everywhere.<lb/>
For in our time, the paint is applied to be<lb/>
so uneven and rough, that one would think<lb/>
they are almost reliefs sculpted in stone.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On the roughness of some in these times.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p048r_5</id>

<ab>
21. Neatness is praiseworthy, for it nourishes<lb/>
the gaze by holding it for a long time,<lb/>
especially if it is held with naturalness,<lb/>
intelligence and boldness, and always looks<lb/>
correct no matter if seen from a distance or up close.<lb/>
Such things attract one; while the eyes<lb/>
are insatiable, the heart cleaves to it with pleasure.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Clean subjects, which preserve intelligence, are praiseworthy, and hold the viewer’s gaze for a long time.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p048r_6</id>

<ab>
22. Concerning the great <i>Titian</i>, we learn<lb/>
from <i>Vasari’s</i> writings, which benefit us well,<lb/>
how in the prime of his Youth, he would<lb/>
diligently execute his works of art<lb/>
with unbelievable neatness.<lb/>
These could not be reproached;<lb/>
on the contrary, they pleased everyone,<lb/>
viewed from a distance and up close.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>The example of Titian; his early works looked good close by and from a distance.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p048r_7</id>

<ab>
23. But, toward the end, he handled his work<lb/>
quite differently, with dabs and rough strokes,<lb/>
which created a natural effect when one stood back<lb/>
and looked from a distance, but not<lb/>
when looking at it close. Various<lb/>
Masters wishing to imitate this in their work<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Titian changed his handling, so that they would be seen only from a distance.</ab>
</div>

</root>