<root>
<page>024r</page>

<div>

<id>p024r_1</id>

<ab>
the strict truth, and said to the King,<lb/>
“It is my Wife, who among all,<lb/>
his heart has set upon.”<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>O<!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p024r_2</id>

<ab>
15. “Ah” (said the king), you who are<lb/>
our beloved friend, should you not permit<lb/>
marriage between your Wife<lb/>
and my Son, who alone (as you know) <lb/>
will inherit our Kingdom and Crown?”<lb/>
“You” (said the other) “who are his loving Father, <lb/>
if he loved <i>Stratonice</i> one could imagine<lb/>
you would not give her to him.”<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p024r_3</id>

<ab>
16. “Oh friend, as my God grants me grace,<lb/>
if any Person had such great virtue<lb/>
that I would transfer my Wife <lb/>
to this lover, for the sake of my Son’s health <lb/>
so that he could live in gilded youth,<lb/>
I would gladly, offer her with love and joy, <lb/>
and also my entire kingdom,” was the King’s reply,<lb/>
with a heart full of feeling and eyes full of tears. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p024r_4</id>

<ab>
17.  Then the Master boldly grasped his right hand,<lb/>
saying, “Be wise and closely watch<lb/>
the prosperity of your house this season,<lb/>
and you will need my help no further.<lb/>
You are this Lovers’ Father, and husband to his beloved,<lb/>
And considering you are King, you must<lb/>
take action as you think best.”<lb/>
At once he [the king] gathered his people in council.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p024r_5</id>

<ab>
18. The King’s decision proceeded, with no opposition<lb/>
at the discretion of Friends or Princes:<lb/>
For his Fatherly love was so effective<lb/>
that she who was first his Wife became his Daughter-in-law.<lb/>
The Son was rid of his heartbreaking agony<lb/>
and further, gained a number of Provinces.<lb/>
This is described in Rhyme from the prose of <i>Plutarch</i><lb/>
To point out how love reveals itself through blushes.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The wondrous love of Seleucus for his Son.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p024r_6</id>

<ab>
19. There is a Proverb to keep in mind now:<lb/>
whither pain, there goes the hand; whither love, there goes the eye.<lb/>
This was from both, for if the head or shin <lb/>
Feels pain, the hand will go there.<lb/>
And the gaze will persevere and go<lb/>
where the heart wills and allows it,<lb/>
following the beloved as they go here and there,<lb/>
just as <i>Clytie</i> did with the Sun’s rays.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>A Proverb: whither love, there the eye: for the eye is the heart’s messenger.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p024r_7</id>

<ab>
20. When <i>Helen</i> lived with <i>Menelaus</i>, <lb/>
<i>Paris</i> of Troy, who was his guest,<lb/>
Often let her know of his desires<lb/>
with his eyes, as the Poets tell, <lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin -->.</ab>

</div>

</root>