<root>
<page>004r</page>

<div>
<id>p004r_1</id>

<ab>33. There is no doubt that <i>Apelles</i>, the Prince of Painters, <lb/>
was modest and courteous, <lb/>
being able to charm <i>Alexander</i> so<lb/>
that he came daily to see him at work. <lb/>
Also worth noting is his courtesy toward <lb/>
<i>Protogenes</i>, for whose Person and work<lb/>
he brought great respect among the <i>Rhodians</i>,<lb/>
as will follow, though not in rhyme.<lb/>


 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Example of the civility of Apelles.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p004r_2</id>

<ab>34. <i>Raphael</i>, too, foremost painter of his time: <lb/>
many good masters earned their wages<lb/>
gladly in his company, <lb/>
working together free from envy, <lb/>
and none was unfriendly to another. <lb/>
The gracious <i>Raphael</i> seemed<lb/>
to dispel vigorously <lb/>
all ignoble, vile thoughts from his spirit.  <lb/>

</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Read of this in the life of Raphael.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p004r_3</id>

<ab>35. So henceforth  “the more one is a painter, the more one is serene.",”<lb/>
not "the more one is a painter, the more one is wild;" <lb/>
those dark mists must be driven from the eyes and vanish, <lb/>
being so clearly and brightly illuminated <lb/>
by two such renowned, noble artists. <lb/>
So now, young Pictorialists, <lb/>
let each accustom himself so much to virtue<lb/>
that he will understand the true nature of Art.<lb/>

</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p004r_4</id>

<ab>36. Two of the most important names, <lb/>
from antiquity and modern times, <lb/>
serve as Examples of how Art and courtesy <lb/>
should always belong together for Artists<lb/>
if you wish to cross the threshold <lb/>
of the temple of immortal Fame;<lb/>
otherwise you run great danger<lb/>
of drowning in the river of Lethe. <lb/>

 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
The fable is taken from Ariosto, <i>Orlando Furioso</i>, cantos 34-35.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p004r_5</id>

<ab>37. For, if the Poets are mistaken, <lb/>
there is an old Man who cannot help going <lb/>
in and out of the house of the three Fates <lb/>
swiftly and ceaselessly, carrying<lb/>
the names of all those whose lives they have cut short;<lb/>
and he runs with an armful (wie het mag benijden)<lb/>
to drop with a great splash into the cold river <i>Lethe</i> <lb/>
where they sink or are washed away.<lb/>
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
A tale from Ariosto, taken from <i>Il furioso</i>, Cantos 34 &amp; 35.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p004r_6</id>

<ab>38. It seems that deer cannot trot as quickly <lb/>
as this old greybeard, back and forth. <lb/>
And along the water that receives his gifts <lb/>
screeching Vultures and Ravens are flying <lb/>
with other birds of various plumage; <lb/>
they fetch from the water, when they descend near it, <lb/>
a few among all the names, <lb/>
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
This old Man you must understand to be Time.
</ab>

</div>

</root>