<root>
<page>042r</page>

<div>

<id>p042r_1</id>

<ab>
on this base, in sorrow and regret, <lb/>
because I was grazing the grass in his field.”<lb/>
“I am the Cow-maker <i>Myron’s</i> Cow,<lb/>
not a wrought Statue, therefore join in <lb/>
poking my flanks and leading me to the plow.”<lb/>
“Why, Myron, do you leave me here?<lb/>
When will you free me to drive me to the stable?”<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Third Epigram.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Fourth Epigram.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_2</id>

<ab>
44. “The Calf shall low and the Bull love me<lb/>
when he sees me; and the young cowherd<lb/>
shall drive me to graze in the green meadows.”<lb/>
“Even if Myron fashioned me from bronze<lb/>
and put me here, I would bellow and roar<lb/>
like a Bull, if only he had given me a tongue.”<lb/>
“A Wasp, seeing this Cow, was deceived:<lb/>
‘I have’ (she said) ‘never stung a harder Cow’s hide.’”<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Fifth Epigram.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Sixth Epigram.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Seventh Epigram.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_3</id>

<ab>
45. “Here Myron holds me, and Herders<lb/>
push and strike me, for they believe that I<lb/>
wish to stay behind for love of a bull.”<lb/>
“Calf, why do you nuzzle at my teats?<lb/>
Art has granted my udders no milk.”<lb/>
“Myron, why do you imprison me on this stone? <lb/>
You could have put me under the yoke and thus<lb/>
I would have pulled the plow through your field.”<lb/>
</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Eighth Epigram.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Ninth Epigram.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Tenth Epigram.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_4</id>

<ab>
46. “Unless they touch my back<lb/>
with their hands, people may behold me<lb/>
at will from afar and close by, and never <lb/>
accuse me of being made from hard bronze.”<lb/>
“If Myron does not release my feet at once<lb/>
from this pedestal, I will not escape death;<lb/>
but if he wishes to free me,<lb/>
I will walk among the flowers, like other Cows.”<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Eleventh Epigram.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Twelfth Epigram.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_5</id>

<ab>
47. Who can feed your hungry desire,<lb/>
O youth, to depict all Animals,<lb/>
not only Lions, but horrifying<lb/>
Monsters and Dragons?  There is nothing better<lb/>
to keep you from going astray than to show you <lb/>
Nature, where you will come upon some model. <lb/>
Notice how each lies, walks, steps, or moves,<lb/>
but treat all according to their essence.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>That there is nothing better, than to paint all things from life, noticing all actions,
and in particular, treating them suitably.
</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_6</id>

<ab>
<b>End of Animals.</b>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_7</id>

<ab>
<b>On Cloth or Drapery. The Tenth Chapter.</b>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p042r_8</id>

<ab>
<b>1. We have before us now a special subject
that shall contribute to the excellence of Painting:
that is, Cloth: which goes well with nakedness
</b>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Cloth, an important part, which contributes to excellence.</ab>
</div>

</root>