<root>
<page>016v</page>

<div>

<id>p016v_1</id>


<ab>
while in front, horses and riders should<lb/> 
tumble over one another, some nicely foreshortened;<lb/> 
here lying in a heap,  bravely struggling,<lb/> 
and there another heap, defeated and weak.<lb/> 
Thus I recount a composition with groups<lb/> 
As I have seen, and I cannot fault it.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p016v_2</id>

<ab>
16.  It is the well-known practice of Tintoretto<lb/> 
to compose thus, with groups or small knots/clusters,<lb/> 
and Michelangelo’s <i>Last Judgment</i> is also<lb/> 
arranged with clusters; though some stain his honor,<lb/> 
not because of these small groupings<lb/> 
but because, for the sake of figures,<lb/> 
he erred in the interest of composition,<lb/> 
for there is no entrance for the eyes.<lb/> 
</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Examples of composition.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p016v_3</id>

<ab>
17. Not revealing, as some would do,<lb/> 
a vista opening to the sky,<lb/> 
and in front something large, as would be desired:<lb/> 
but how should this not be taken for the best,<lb/> 
seeing this work flooded full of art<lb/> 
from the learned hand of <i>Buonarrotti</i>,<lb/> 
so many different positions of styles<lb/> 
of nudes, which were his concern.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Michelangelo, in his Last Judgement, paid more attention to his Figures than to his composition.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p016v_4</id>

<ab>
18. Also one can easily understand<lb/> 
that the law of composition is for the people,<lb/> 
but that it is not for the people to preserve the law;<lb/> 
for laws serve the people for good,<lb/> 
so that no shame may befall them,<lb/> 
What else had the laws to command?<lb/> 
So we may excuse such Masters<lb/> 
who pay more attention to figures than to composition.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Laws serve people for the best.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p016v_5</id>


<ab>
19. It is very commendable to seek <lb/> 
attractiveness in figures, and never to stray from this,<lb/> 
but there is a greater abundance<lb/> 
of excellence when the composition<lb/> 
is similar to this as well;<lb/> 
and just as the sound of musicians<lb/> 
makes harmony from singing and playing,<lb/> 
so here, too, do many different figures.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p016v_6</id>


<ab>
20. Nature’s beauty lies in variety.<lb/> 
One sees this as the earth, blooming with <lb/> 
almost a thousand colors, displays itself for praise,<lb/> 
vying with the starry throne of heaven, <lb/> 
as appealing delight can be perceived<lb/> 
in many other things: for without a care,<lb/> 
people enjoy themselves at an assortment<lb/> 
Of food and drink at a table. <lb/> 
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Nature’s beauty lies in variety.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p016v_7</id>


<ab>
21. And as for history, there is much to consider:<lb/> 
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>
</root>