<root>
<page>027r</page>

<div>

<id>p027r_1</id>

<ab>
one could not easily turn one’s eyes away.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p027r_2</id>

<ab>
50. A <i>Meleager</i>, carried in death,<lb/>
was also greatly admired by the Romans. <lb/>
There one sees depicted how each bearer,<lb/>
is also a mourner, with a sorrowful heart;<lb/>
and the strength of the labor is well suggested<lb/>
and in that dead <i>Corpse</i> above all<lb/>
the art is not the lesser or insignificant; it seemed<lb/>
fully powerless and dead, in trunk, limbs and fingers.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Gual. Rivi. Book 3.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p027r_3</id>

<ab>
51. I have in my memory a Modern piece,<lb/>
on the Capitoline Hill, with signed of such grace<lb/>
in emotions, to the glory of the Painter:<lb/>
and it is the history of the combat<lb/>
of the three <i>Horatii</i> and the <i>Curiatii</i>,<lb/>
there one saw <i>Tullus</i> the Roman King, alas,<lb/>
sitting with his Lords, justly sad<lb/>
that his last Man had to fight against three.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>This was an old-fashioned Painting in which Sorrow, Joy, and Death were very naturally depicted.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p027r_4</id>

<ab>
52. And it seemed that he mourned his two Brothers,<lb/>
his Champions, lying there defeated. <lb/>
It seemed too that the Painter knew the correct manner<lb/>
of depicting, with wonderful art, the dying actions of these Knights.<lb/>
Also it seemed that the hearts of <i>Mettus</i> and the <i>Alba</i> <i>Longans</i><lb/>
swam joyfully in a sea of gladness<lb/>
Since their warriors (as it appeared) carried the day.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p027r_5</id>

<ab>
53. This was depicted in such a distinctive <lb/>
calm manner that many were amazed. <lb/>
Also, it is not at all despised<lb/>
for being so different from our own time.<lb/>
For it is perhaps a century old.<lb/>
The color and handling are exceptional;<lb/>
one sees very few like it<lb/>
in painting the essence of Emotions.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>This piece now (I believe) belongs to Emperor Rudolp.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p027r_6</id>

<ab>
54. From the excellent and faultless Brueghel <lb/>
there is yet in a Massacre of the Innocents<lb/>
a deathly pale Mother, overwhelmed in a swoon,<lb/>
yes, a wretched family beseeching a Herald<lb/>
to spare a child’s life, in whom <lb/>
can be espied compassion well enough,<lb/>
but with pained feeling he displays the King’s proclamation <lb/>
that mercy must be shown toward none.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p027r_7</id>

<ab>
55. Thus, learning of surely endless examples, <lb/>
Ancient and Modern,<lb/>
let your heart be aflame with burning desire <lb/>
for these Emotions as proper Teachers,<lb/>
or the Soul, which Art keeps within itself<lb/>
like the kernel of a nut, <lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Depicting the emotions, the Soul of Art.</ab>

</div>

</root>