<root>
<page>054r</page>

<div>

<id>p054r_1</id>

<ab>
“There stood a Horse sumptuously ornamented<lb/>
with Purple and Gold, who, bold and superb,<lb/>
bit his bridle until foam came from his mouth.<lb/>
Then at last came <i>Dido</i>, <lb/>
a gilded diadem in her fine hair,<lb/>
And beautifully colored silk clothes,<lb/>
Under an exquisite Sidonian Cloak<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054r_2</id>

<ab>
19. …and carrying, among other things, a golden Quiver.”<lb/>
No more than one wishing to depict the boasting <i>Croesus</i><lb/>
when he would proudly impress <i>Solon</i><lb/>
with the abundance of his fortune,<lb/>
showing him clothes, jewels and treasures.<lb/>
Since it is noticeable that gold highlights on flat areas<lb/>
make a dark effect instead of glittering,<lb/>
it is best to accomplish this with colors.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Gold highlights on flat areas look dark.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p054r_3</id>

<ab>
20. Using Gold to represent Gold is not justified,<lb/>
for it will fit poorly within the picture,<lb/>
although in the past it was wasted a great deal.<lb/>
But there is nothing to despise, and much to praise,<lb/>
In ornamenting with Gold <lb/>
on the frames, borders and edges, above and below, <lb/>
with masks, arabesques, curled ribbons, and gilding.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054r_4</id>

<ab>
21. <i>Gualterus</i> <i>Riverus</i>, a very learned man,<lb/>
wished a painting, done with skill by expert hands,<lb/>
to be not only framed in gold,<lb/>
but further enhanced with precious stones.<lb/>
This is right and good. In his writings, he considers<lb/>
such a piece to be well-painted,<lb/>
but he did not tolerate that gilding <lb/>
was also on the painting itself.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>That one can ornament the outside of a well-made Painting without too much cost. </ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054r_5</id>

<ab>
22. Next to Gold, among all the metals,<lb/>
Silver has the proper principal place<lb/>
for its value and its beauty, glittering <lb/>
with pure gleams.  It would take a long time<lb/>
to recount what God, in his Law,<lb/>
had everyone make in His honor. <lb/>
But see what Silver signifies: because it is like white,<lb/>
it indicates innocence and purity without sin.<lb/>
</ab>

<margin>right-middle</margin>On Silver, which is perceived as white, and what it means. </ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Exodus 36 [:24-25, 30]</ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Exodus 38 [:23, 26]</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054r_6</id>

<ab>
23. Such was the pure Lamb, full of honor,<lb/>
white, chosen among thousands for its beauty;<lb/>
its garments from Tabor gleaming white as snow,<lb/>
The Angels of the Lord appeared in white.<lb/>
The pure Truth of the just<lb/>
Was clad all in white. And above all,<lb/>
Our eyes always love to behold innocent Youth<lb/>
Women and Maidens clad in white.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Canticles 5 [:10]</ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Mark 9 [:3] </ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Acts 1 [:10]</ab>

</div>

</root>