<root>
<page>053r</page>

<div>

<id>p053r_1</id>

<ab>
whose brilliance is unsurpassed; and <i>Phoebus</i><lb/>
was named for his golden hair, yes, always gold.<lb/>
The usefulness of Gold is manifold,<lb/>
Men use it in many ways, <lb/>
but its misuse comes from intemperate desire.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Gold is useful, though misused by the intemperate desires of Men.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053r_2</id>

<ab>
7. Then, for this reason, no color can be <lb/>
more beautiful than the clear color of gold.<lb/>
Emperors, Kings and powerful people<lb/>
Have their Scepters, necklaces, Crowns,<lb/>
And many ornaments made of Gold.<lb/>
Borders on cloaks, and cloth of gold,<lb/>
And clothing shot through with gold threads,<lb/>
Which King <i>Attalus</i> first applied.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Why Gold is of higher worth.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Gold was used.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Gold was first used in weaving by Attalus.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p053r_3</id>

<ab>
8. And <i>Attalus’</i> work has retained its name. <lb/>
But in <i>Babylon</i> there was one who invented<lb/>
embroidery of many colors mingled <lb/>
with gold threads, which is why<lb/>
this kind of work is called Babylonian,<lb/>
Costly, and worth many thousands of pounds.<lb/>
Indeed, the Emperor Nero paid a million Sesterces<lb/>
for a wrought garment of this sort.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>A gold border was first invented in Babylon. Joshua 7:21.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053r_4</id>

<ab>
9. The Holy Scripture bears witness, without dispute,<lb/>
to very costly golden Garments,<lb/>
and how wise Solomon, rich in goods,<lb/>
arrayed God’s House entirely in pure gold;<lb/>
even the floor was covered with golden tiles.<lb/>
In sum, we can well imagine what ravishing, <lb/>
immeasurable beauty, yes, what wonderful magnificence<lb/>
that pure golden yellow shining there must have been.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>I Kings 6:22-30. Astonishing beauty of Solomon’s Temple.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053r_5</id>

<ab>
10. According to Scripture, Gold<lb/>
signifies tested faith, strong and active,<lb/>
with which the Bride of the Lord <lb/>
is entirely arrayed, just as, likewise,<lb/>
the bracelets of <i>Rebecca</i> indicate.<lb/>
For he who was faithful and true<lb/>
advised a community weakened in faith,<lb/>
to buy from him Gold purified in the fire.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>What gold means in Scripture. Psalm 45:14, Genesis 24:22.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Apoc. 3: 18.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p053r_6</id>

<ab>
11. There would be much to gloss from the poets,<lb/>
from the golden branch of <i>Virgil</i>, and the like.<lb/>
But hear how the Heralds in their emblazoning<lb/>
Of noble coats of arms explain colors:<lb/>
this supreme metal indicates one’s wealth,<lb/>
wisdom, nobility, and generosity,<lb/>
while they are given new meaning.<lb/>
according to adjacent colors.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Virgil’s golden branch indicates wisdom.
In the coats of arms of Nobility, Gold indicates wealth, wisdom and generosity.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p053r_7</id>

<ab>
12. Next to blue, which is its favorite companion,<lb/>
it signifies, for the wearing of Livery, <lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Gold next to blue means enjoyment of the world’s pleasure.</ab>
</div>


</root>