<root>
<page>003v</page>

<div>

<id>p003v_1</id>


<ab>people’s eyes so that their spirits, from dwelling <lb/>
in their hearts, attach themselves to it,  <lb/>
would also deserve to win the friendship of everyone<lb/>
by being virtuous and honorable, which is an Art <lb/>
above all other Arts, in order to obtain good favor, <lb/>
grace and friendship, according to his heart's desire, <lb/>
from God and all People.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Just as the artful painter, with his work, lures People to look, he should live honorably with art, attracting each one to friendship.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p003v_2</id>

<ab>28. Among all who bear the name of Painter,  <lb/>
noble courtesy should prevail,  <lb/>
which can often move  <lb/>
the hearts of Peasants and touch them  <lb/>
with its decent and winning ways.  <lb/>
In short, all ordered and kind <lb/>
modesty must be especially included <lb/>
in the name or the word painterly. <lb/>
</ab>ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>All modesty included in the word Painterly.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p003v_3</id>

<ab>29. Thus painters, being Painterly,  <lb/>
should therefore discard, flatten and drive out <lb/>
all envy, dispute and discord <lb/>
with gentle, wise, sensible words<lb/>
and not with fighting, evil words and quarrelling, <lb/>
like Fishwives at the Market, <lb/>
who often rob one another’s reputations <lb/>
and throw baskets at one another’s heads.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Painters should not fight or quarrel but settle all disputes with wisdom.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p003v_4</id>

<ab>30. Nor should one follow the example of the Wagoners, <lb/>
with whom courtesy is seldom encountered<lb/>
and who hurt one another with fists and knives in their quarrels,<lb/>
for ignorance is the mother of discord;<lb/>
but the true nature of Art causes <lb/>
those who have risen in the Arts<lb/>
to possess the greatest courtesy.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Ignorance is the mother of discord.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p003v_5</id>


<ab>31. Since the Greeks’ and Romans’ Dedication<lb/> 
to <i>Pictura</i> spread with such fire <lb/> 
that they forbade, with strict orders, <lb/> 
anyone other than <lb/> 
nobly-born children to be taught painting, <lb/> 
it is fitting that, to honor Art, <lb/> 
all virtue and courtesy should accompany <lb/> 
those who follow the Noble Brush.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Read about the life of the Macedonian painter Pamphilus. Plutarch also says that Emilius Paulus, among other noble artists, taught his sons how to paint and sculpt.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p003v_6</id>


<ab>32. <i>Jove's</i> daughters, the three <i>Graces</i>, <lb/>
were depicted with one seeming about to walk away <lb/>
with her back turned to you; and then <lb/>
there were two frontally depicted, at some distance.<lb/>
This signifies that for a single act of friendship <lb/>
we receive two: hence courtesy <lb/>
should never slacken but be ever bolder,<lb/>
to serve more profit everywhere.<lb/>
 </ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --> </ab>

</div>
</root>