<root>
<page>011v</page>

<div>

<id>p011v_1</id>


<ab>
is barely two faces wide, as opposed to the man’s.
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p011v_2</id>

<ab>
14. But women should not show hardness<lb/>
in the muscles, which, as a whole, <lb/>
must softly withdraw into the face or nicely disappear, <lb/>
plump of flesh, with folds and dimples in the hands, as in children.<lb/>
Now we should consider the children: <lb/>
They are five heads tall, but smaller accordingly;<lb/>
three heads to the genitals,<lb/>
to the thighs and calves, two.<lb/>
</ab>
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>Women have plumper flesh than men.</ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>Children are five heads high; and at three years old they are half as tall as they will become.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p011v_3</id>

<ab>
15. You will encounter different proportions in life:<lb/>
short of length, and slim. <lb/>
Children are (as Pliny tells us)<lb/>
grown to half their height in three years.<lb/>
Now, young painters, accept these few things.<lb/>
I shall instruct you further in how to place a figure<lb/>
so that it does not waver, and how to make it act and move,<lb/>
in order to execute everything properly.<lb/>
</ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>Figures 9, 10 and even 12 heads high can be seen in Michelangelo, to achieve grace in bending and turning; he said that the compass must be in the eye and not in the hand.</ab>
<ab><margin>bottom</margin><b>End of Proportion</b></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p011v_4</id>

<ab><b>CHAPTER IV: Pose, balance, and the proper execution of a figure.</b></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p011v_5</id>


<ab>
1. Heaven, being kind and bountiful, <lb/>
has granted noble Nature, <lb/>
along with other essential gifts,<lb/> 
the virtue of beauty, moral and artistic,<lb/>
which is utterly pleasing to the eye.<lb/>
If we examine the origin and means, <lb/>
we discover in the circumstances why<lb/>
Nature’s beauty is perfect beauty.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Nature is beautiful, because of the various virtues or gifts she possesses.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p011v_6</id>


<ab>
2. It can be clearly discerned <lb/>
in the many manifestations of natural things<lb/>
that beauty is disfigured and diminished <lb/>
when secondary failures occur,<lb/>
which will lead us to our intended subject:<lb/>
how sometimes we painters, despite working diligently,<lb/>
cannot make a figure that satisfies us,<lb/>
yet without understanding why.<lb/>

</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Beauty is diminished when any subsidiary elements are missing.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Sometimes young painters make a figure that displeases them, without knowing what is deficient; therefore, the following instructions.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p011v_7</id>


<ab>
3. While the contours of our figures reveal enough relief,<lb/>
sometimes the forceful movement<lb/>
of a pose fails, or the Figure leans<lb/>
as if about to fall, or it has a peculiar,<lb/>
unstable quality. In order to avoid<lb/>
these things in the future, which are so wrong,<lb/>
it is necessary for instruction to be given.<lb/>
</ab>	



</div>
</root>