<root>
<page>045v</page>

<div>

<id>p045v_1</id>


<ab>
2. If we succeed well in this part of our Art,<lb/>
it will make our work more remarkably beautiful, <lb/>
As with the maiden <i>Glycera</i> of <i>Sicyone</i>,<lb/>
seller of flower garlands, who knew how to arrange<lb/>
her Flowers ten thousand ways <lb/>
with an extraordinary sense of their nature, <lb/>
particularly cheerful colors, which so delighted<lb/>
the Painter <i>Pausias</i> that he fell in love with her.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045v_2</id>

<ab>
3. Let us vary our Fabrics in the same manner,<lb/>
for <i>Pausias</i>, seeing this this artful arrangement,<lb/>
began to paint her Bouquets and Crowns<lb/>
and became fully skilled in these matters.<lb/>
At last he toiled much further, <lb/>
and with great pleasure made a portrait of her <lb/>
assembling her Crowns.<lb/>
This piece was called <i>Stephanoplokos</i>.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045v_3</id>

<ab>
4. And so, in regard to varying colors, <lb/>
we have proposed a discourse of Flowers,<lb/>
which are painted in variety by nature,<lb/>
in fragrant Spring, in the valleys of Tempe,<lb/>
as if scattered on a green Carpet.<lb/>
And however many thousands of flowers are opened,<lb/>
scarcely one of them will still be green.<lb/>
This occurs because of variation, <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Learn from Flowers how to vary colors.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045v_4</id>

<ab>
5. yet varying from green to green, even with each<lb/>
standing out, will lead to beauty.<lb/>
Whether red, blue, purple, or white as milk,<lb/>
 Look also at the leaves of Trees and shrubs, which,<lb/>
though themselves all green, have great variation.<lb/>
Now, lifting our eyes from these meadows,<lb/>
we see a variation that ought to be noticed<lb/>
day and night, in the vaulted Sky.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The variation, or dividing, of colors, to observe in all living things.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045v_5</id>

<ab>
6. I let the blushing dawn,<lb/>
the herald of <i>Phoebus</i>, pass by,<lb/>
with her splendid variety, early and late;<lb/>
but to see beyond (it is worth observing)<lb/>
how the golden Sun, illuminating all the World,<lb/>
brings in and leads away the Years<lb/>
in a blue field of azure; and how the Moon and Stars,<lb/>
his Vassals, shine in the blue as brightly as gold!<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045v_6</id>

<ab>
7. Yellow and blue go well side by side;<lb/>
you might color your fabrics this way.<lb/>
Red and green, too, love each other wonderfully. <lb/>
Red next to blue, to make a change, <lb/>
are also well suited; purple has no fear<lb/>
of being near yellow, green is refreshed<lb/>
next to white–indeed, white fits with all colors,<lb/>
just as Vines go well with fields of Wheat.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Which colors love one another. </ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045v_7</id>

<ab>
8. That Nature shows us how to create variety<lb/>
is easily seen in all things<lb/>
which offer joyful embellishment to the eyes.<lb/>
For example, talkative Parrots,<lb/>
birds, shells, and still more creatures,<lb/>
show how all colors agree with one another.<lb/>
Thus Nature, which makes us all wise,<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Nature shows us how to create variation in colors.</ab>

</div>

</root>