<root>
<page>051v</page>

<div>

<id>p051v_1</id>


<ab>
in the early summer, as the fields bloom<lb/>
full of cheery colors, with a fine diversity;<lb/>
that even <i>Solomon</i> himself did not wear<lb/>
adornment as exquisite as a Lily,<lb/>
as the Lord says in the Gospel.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example of flowers.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p051v_2</id>

<ab>
16. Colors in the figures of young People,<lb/>
especially Women, miraculously cause <lb/>
many hearts to swim in the Sea of pleasure,<lb/>
believing that they see the Graces play<lb/>
around the mouth, cheeks, and loving eyes<lb/>
of Women, for whom, in fierce battles,<lb/>
many a bold Hero has bowed in surrender.<lb/>
This proves the power of Colors.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Of Women.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p051v_3</id>

<ab>
17. <i>Scipio</i>, and <i>Alexander</i> the great,<lb/>
have great fame in the affairs of war,<lb/>
one as well as the other;<lb/>
yet they are considered more valiant<lb/>
for overcoming their lust for bodies of beautiful Women.<lb/>
Some have preferred blindness <lb/>
than to look at these women of beautiful colors,<lb/>
fearing they would lose mastery of their passions.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Scipio and Alexander were renowned more for their mastery of their passions than for their military victories.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p051v_4</id>

<ab>
18. It is useful here, for the glory of Colors,<lb/>
to recall the art of Writing, with black on white,<lb/>
by which Men keep in memory<lb/>
the Arts, science, and much of History.<lb/>
Writing engenders strife, bloodshed and pain;<lb/>
it also creates peace, alliance, and joy in the heart.<lb/>
Indeed, even Men who scattered far from one another<lb/>
Speak together through mute messengers.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The Usefulness of the Art of Writing.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p051v_5</id>

<ab>
19. <i>Girolamo</i> <i>Benzoni</i> of <i>Milan</i><lb/>
wrote in this regard, in service to our subject,<lb/>
how the simple people of India,<lb/>
sent as subjects with letters <lb/>
from Spaniards to other Spaniards,<lb/>
could not understand, <lb/>
however they discussed it among themselves,<lb/>
how a white object covered with black could also speak. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>This Benzo spent fourteen years in the West Indies; I translated his Book.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p051v_6</id>

<ab>
20. They know nothing of writing or reading.<lb/>
<i>Atahualpa</i> himself, great Aristocrat,<lb/>
The powerful King of Peru, <lb/>
instructed in religion by a Monk, <lb/>
asked the Friar, how he knew<lb/>
the Christ, who gave his life for us,<lb/>
also created the World. The latter answered<lb/>
that his Breviary told him so.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>West-Indians do not know of writing.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p051v_7</id>

<ab>
21. With the Monk’s permission,<lb/>
<i>Atahualpa</i> took the book and stared at it fixedly; <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Atahualpa believed that Books must speak.</ab>

</div>

</root>