<root>
<page>030v</page>

<div>

<id>p030v_1</id>


<ab>
through what I have related here,<lb/>
to help silence those who believe<lb/>
that the Reflection is forced into a bow<lb/>
from the hollow clouds.<lb/>
Because at <i>Tivoli</i>, springing up very high,<lb/>
there are Various Fountains of surpassing beauty,<lb/>
and I have also seen Rainbows appear in them.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Also in the ponds at Tivoli, where the Fountains play.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p030v_2</id>

<ab>
18. …in the humid air, through which <lb/>
the brilliantly shining Sun pierces its rays. <lb/>
But from where does the Rainbow summon<lb/>
its beautiful colors? If those who have<lb/>
left us their writings on this subject<lb/>
are not wrong, it receives them itself <lb/>
from the clouds, and carries them <lb/>
from the Air and fire mingling with them.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On where the rainbow receives its colors.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p030v_3</id>

<ab>
19. <i>Ezekiel</i>, a blessed Prophet,<lb/>
saw the glory of the Lord shining everywhere,<lb/>
just as the Rainbow, when it has rained,<lb/>
reveals itself in the clouds to men’s eyes.<lb/>
One may well think too of John: <lb/>
He heard a voice sound like a Trumpet<lb/>
and saw, in his vision, the Rainbow<lb/>
enthroned, lovely as an emerald.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p030v_4</id>

<ab>
20. Beholding the form of the Rainbow,<lb/>
said Jesus ben Sirach, they will praise Him<lb/>
whose creature or creation it is,<lb/>
for it has (said he) a very beautiful pure color,<lb/>
In the same way, <i>Simon</i>, the High Priest, <lb/>
when he brought the veil to decorate the temple, <lb/>
compared it to the Rainbow,<lb/>
with its lovely colored light.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Syrach. 43.12</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p030v_5</id>
<ab>
21. Also what the Poets say of <i>Iris</i>,<lb/>
how her garment has many colors<lb/>
and brightly lustrous: this is all <lb/>
in total what is seen in the Rainbow.<lb/>
In order to depict it, one should<lb/>
mark well how the colors stand out,<lb/>
how finely they flow in drifting away<lb/>
and seem to grow out of one another.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The Poets’ Iris, herald of Juno, is the Rainbow.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p030v_6</id>


<ab>
22. At hand is purple, then incarnadine,<lb/>
or pale white, to add color well;<lb/>
then orange, or glorious red, <lb/>
then mastic yellow, then delicate green,<lb/>
then clear azure, like the neck feathers of a Peacock,<lb/>
and following again, purple. To dominate<lb/>
with such a variegated cloak is the custom<lb/>
for this leading messenger of <i>Juno</i>.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The colors of the Rainbow. </ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p030v_7</id>


<ab>
23. Each practitioner of mute 
</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

</root>