<root>
<page>053v</page>

<div>

<id>p053v_1</id>


<ab>
the enjoyment of the World’s pleasures and delights;<lb/>
but next to grey, it only means disturbance<lb/>
of whose who torment themselves with anxious worry,<lb/>
next to green, hope with delight, <lb/>
next to violet, consolation of requited love,<lb/>
next to black, patience and perseverance in love.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Next to grey, worry.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Next to violet, consolation of love.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Next to black, patience and perseverance in love.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p053v_2</id>

<ab>
13. Next to flesh color, this gold-yellow <lb/>
signifies moderate wealth: by itself, at times,<lb/>
it indicates a rational man, of good quality,<lb/>
of a moderate and wise demeanor,<lb/>
also of good counsel, and everywhere at ease.<lb/>
But among all pure precious stones,<lb/>
it is Topaz (to be precise) to which <lb/>
this noblest gold color is most compared.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Next to flesh color, moderate wealth.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Next to black, patience and perseverance in love.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053v_3</id>

<ab>
14. Yellow is thus a beautiful and joyful color,<lb/>
bright, and clear in aspect as it approaches white.<lb/>
During the times of both Moses and Solomon, <lb/>
there was a veil, or a great curtain, <lb/>
artfully made and wrought of silk,<lb/>
but yellow was the principal color.<lb/>
So it does not seem contrary to propriety<lb/>
To present yellow as the first of the colors.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Yellow as the principal color.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053v_4</id>

<ab>
15. While the ancient Painters only had four sorts<lb/>
of colors, as we have said earlier,<lb/>
yellow was one of them. <lb/>
Without it, what would they have invented<lb/>
To give their work any appearance? <lb/>
However, we already have four different kinds<lb/>
Of yellow, aside from Ocher:<lb/>
Masticot, brown-yellow, and two Orpiments.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053v_5</id>

<ab>
16. Minium can also serve sufficiently<lb/>
as orange-yellow, that is, the color of gold;<lb/>
one can use it with Masticot <lb/>
to create decoration. For it is ridiculous<lb/>
to use a great deal of Gold, one must shun it<lb/>
in one’s work. I have no power to forbid it entirely,<lb/>
but it is better to agree <lb/>
to produce decoration with colors. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>To decorate with Gold is despised by certain writers; yet that which looks good, is good. 
Art is to adorn well and with moderation, and it does not matter what means are used for a good look</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053v_6</id>

<ab>
17. While in earlier times some believed<lb/>
that their work with Gold to be beautiful–<lb/>
which was highly praised by those who lacked intelligence – <lb/>
in these times it would be considered disfiguring <lb/>
rather than an embellishment.<lb/>
Thus wishing to depict <i>Dido</i> <lb/>
leaving the hunt with <i>Aeneas</i> of Troy, <lb/>
one would not need to be very generous with Gold.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>I copy this from others. Let each have his own freedom. </ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p053v_7</id>

<ab>
18. Even if Virgil wrote as follows: <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

</root>