<root>
<page>050r</page>

<div>

<id>p050r_1</id>

<ab>
and use in its place a very pure and light ocher;<lb/>
as I said above, this is more advisable<lb/>
than overloading one’s flesh tone<lb/>
with this heavy color that discolors the highlights<lb/>
and is bad to use, since it dries too fast.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050r_2</id>

<ab>
42. You should also renounce Minium and Spanish green,<lb/>
And Orpiment, poisonous by nature.<lb/>
I advise you to clean your Brushes well,<lb/>
or keep some for clear blue Fabric<lb/>
or Skies, and moreover, if you can do so,<lb/>
be sure to provide yourself over time<lb/>
with pure colors and learn to keep them ready,<lb/>
as one who holds art in esteem and honors it.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Avoiding Minium, Spanish green, and Orpiment.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050r_3</id>

<ab>
43. The smalts must be well absorbed. <lb/>
To achieve this, some prick very dense holes<lb/>
In their panels with needles. <lb/>
Others cover their work with some rough paper,<lb/>
which they leave there to draw out<lb/>
the oil, and some others paint<lb/>
with Poppyseed oil, while others<lb/>
use Oil prepared according to their own experience.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Smalts must be absorbed, to discolor less.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050r_4</id>

<ab>
<b>End of Painting well, or the Application of Colors.</b>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p050r_5</id>

<ab>
<b>Chapter XIII. Origin, Nature, Power and Effects of Colors.<lb/>
The Thirteenth Chapter.</b>
</ab>

<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p050r_6</id>

<ab>
1. In the beginning, as all creatures<lb/>
receive from their highly praised Creator<lb/>
origin, shape, and being, <lb/>
all visible that the eye can encompass,<lb/>
how numerous diverse and how strange in nature– <lb/>
all of them have received their color <lb/>
from this most artful Sculptor and Painter. <lb/>
How can the origin of the Colors be more abundant?<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>All have their colors from God.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p050r_7</id>

<ab>
2. But when darkness was in the depths, <lb/>
or, as the poets suppose about Chaos,<lb/>
before things were ordered,<lb/>
when the Sky was devoured by Darkness<lb/>
all together and upside down,<lb/>
the colors, with their various names,<lb/>
did not yet exist, or, if they did,<lb/>
were fully hidden, still to be revealed.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Colors emerged with the creation of the world.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p050r_8</id>

<ab>
3. Surely, everywhere the Darkness <lb/>
can dominate or defeat the Light in battle,<lb/>
no colors are prevented, but the sight<lb/>
is neither strong nor keen enough <lb/>
to cut through the thick black darkness.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Darkness prevailed and prevented the colors from being distinguished.</ab>
</div>

</root>