<root>
<page>014r</page>

<div>

<id>p014r_1</id>

<ab>
so that the leg serves as a prop;<lb/>
for a person disposes himself so that <lb/>
his limbs stay balanced while stooping and bending,<lb/>
as some learned people will attest.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p014r_2</id>

<ab>
28. Where one shoulder carries the weight, <lb/>
the leg on the same side cannot fiddle with its position<lb/>
but must stay rigid under the burden.<lb/>
Further, also see to it that the figure<lb/>
does not stride beyond what is natural and graceful;<lb/>
that is, when feet are placed more than a foot’s length apart.<lb/>
Keep in mind that the Ancients paid attention to standing<lb/>
as well as to taking a step and walking. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On the action of walking, and on a standing pose.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p014r_3</id>

<ab>
29. With a beautiful and graceful manner,<lb/>
swerving outward only a little or hardly at all,<lb/>
they present to all Art-lovers<lb/>
a pleasant movement, indicating action,<lb/>
which must be satisfying to everyone.<lb/>
Now it happens sometimes, that figures<lb/>
reaching high up must rest<lb/>
on the balls of their feet or on their toes <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --> </ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p014r_4</id>

<ab>
30. Like the exuberant nymphs, female figures<lb/>
dancing, some leaping from the ground<lb/>
with both legs, others on their toes: <lb/>
to render this well will make our work lovely.<lb/>
And if we need an example, <lb/>
<i>Canachus</i>, who was in earlier times valued for his art,<lb/>
(as Pliny reveals to us)<lb/>
a sculptor in stone and bronze.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
On pretty attitudes in dancing, jumping, and the like.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p014r_5</id>

<ab>
31. He had made a stag, in bronze or stone,<lb/>
which aroused such wonder,<lb/>
standing so artfully and lightly on its legs,<lb/>
that one could have pulled a thread<lb/>
under all four feet. From behind it seemed <lb/>
to be lightly stretching up on its toes<lb/>
into a joyous leap, while <lb/>
from the front, it seemed to rest on its heels.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>An example of a bronze stag.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p014r_6</id>

<ab>
32. In moving figures one should precisely<lb/>
pay attention to Nature, so that the limbs are working fully, <lb/>
whether hands or fingers, on the lute or harp,<lb/>
play, shoot, or throw something,<lb/>
cut, drag, carry, dig, or delve.<lb/>
All the limbs must move together<lb/>
in a walking figure, and furthermore, <lb/>
all actions depicting movement should be rendered artfully.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Depicting the limbs of a figure playing, shooting, throwing, and so on, according to art.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p014r_7</id>

<ab>
33. Here as an example we would follow<lb/>
that artful work by <i>Demon of Athens</i>. <sup><comment>2 note. See Miedema 457. A misinterpretation of Pliny on Parrhasius</comment></sup><lb/>
of two hoplite soldiers, on of whom seems<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Example of a walking pose, or a weary figure.
</ab>

</div>
</root>