<root>
<page>007r</page>

<div>
<id>p007r_1</id>

<ab>
who have always greatly exalted our art, <lb/>
are generally neither Traitors nor Thieves, <lb/>
but cultivated and overflowing with courtesy,<lb/>
though with open mouth and closed fist; <lb/>
for there is almost no Nation under the Sun <lb/>
without particular faults and graces.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
The nature of the Italians.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_2</id>

<ab>
69. But if you do travel, do not let it happen <lb/>
without your desire and your Parents’ consent.<lb/>
Avoid small Inns and bad company, <lb/>
take care not to be seen with much money,<lb/>
and keep quiet about being on a long journey.<lb/>
Be honorable and polite, make no disturbance, <lb/>
always have good money, but think twice<lb/>
before lending much to your cunning Countrymen.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Instructions for young painters to put into practice while traveling.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_3</id>

<ab>
70. Learn Peoples' customs everywhere <lb/>
to follow the good and avoid the bad.<lb/>
Set forth early and also, find lodgings early,<lb/>
and to avoid diseases and vermin, <lb/>
carefully examine the beds and sheets. <lb/>
But especially, never engage with <lb/>
loose Women, for apart from the sin, <lb/>
you would be defiled for your whole life.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
There is much ruin from loose Women. 
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_4</id>

<ab>
71.Coming to Italy, you should sometimes, <lb/>
like the Falcon, cover your eyes<lb/>
before the beautiful <i>Circe</i>, with all her trickery.<lb/>
As for the work, it is making frescoes<lb/>
Of landscapes with <i>Grotesques</i>,<lb/>
because the Italians always suppose us <lb/>
to be good at this, and themselves, good at figures. <lb/>
I hope that we can steal their share.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
What is given to us by God can be taken away.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_5</id>

<ab>
72. Indeed, I trust that here I cherish no idle hope; <lb/>
they themselves see enough proof<lb/>
in canvas, stone, and copper plates.<lb/>	
So, Youths, take courage<lb/>
although there is so far to go;<lb/>
do your best, so we can reach our goal: <lb/> 
that they will no longer say, in their language, <lb/>
“The Flemish cannot make figures.”<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Recommended to do one’s best, so the Italians will take back their Proverb
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_6</id>

<ab>
73. On the way back you must not be negligent; <lb/>
rather, visit <i>Germany</i> or another country<lb/>
where there is more Money than Art, <lb/>
and (since conditions are not bad <lb/>
in the French lands) Provence, Brittany, <lb/>
all of France, Burgundy, and Spain:<lb/>
everywhere one can earn <lb/>
fine Indian gold and white metal.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
On the way back from Italy one should visit other countries, to come home having earned much money; then one is welcome.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p007r_7</id>

<ab>
74. To bring home a large quantity of coins <lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!-- Nothing in margin -->
</ab>

</div>
</root>