<root>
<page>047r</page>

<div>

<id>p047r_1</id>

<ab>
and realize their intentions with honor.<lb/>
This may be suitable for the <i>Caesars</i> of Painting,<lb/>
who progress in Art without rest, <lb/>
and increase their riches by painting boldly.<lb/>
But even if one could learn to handle<lb/>
colors with such courage, never hesitating,<lb/>
it will not be suited to everyone.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Painting at once without drawing will not be suited to everyone. </ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p047r_2</id>

<ab>
7. there are others who with great difficulty and labor,<lb/>
sketch out or draw, hoping to gather<lb/>
their subjects into an unbroken composition,<lb/>
then draw clearly and precisely <lb/>
what they have fixed fully in their minds,<lb/>
on the primer with a thinned paint<lb/>
that flows easily, or tracing neatly with Graphite<lb/>
and wiping their work clean, leave it spotless.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Bringing things together painstakingly, and then transferring them neatly, is advantageous in painting.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p047r_3</id>

<ab>
8. Yes, they make all things firmly and wisely,<lb/>
surfaces as well as contours, by measuring, <lb/>
without making a crooked line in error.<lb/>
This goes well, and could not fail at all, <lb/>
and is a great benefit in painting.<lb/>
And for the painting to look good in all respects,<lb/>
and not discolor, they set down<lb/>
well mixed colors, each in its place<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Putting each color in its place from the beginning, so as not to fade. </ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p047r_4</id>

<ab>
9. However, the Italians, no matter what they undertake<lb/>
–whether painting on a wall, or on panel–<lb/>
from elaborate sketches, with care, diligence,<lb/>
and good study, they make cartoons,<lb/>
which are the same size as their works in all parts,<lb/>
they work the plaster with the ends of their brushes<lb/>
or another sharp object that lends itself to it.<lb/>
They go back over all the lines by pressing hard<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Italians make cartoons, that is, papers as large as the work, neatly drawn, so that they can trace through them.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p047r_5</id>

<ab>
10. so that it transfers to the work<lb/>
without breaks, and succeeds well.<lb/>
For an Oil-painting, they first coat <lb/>
the back of the cartoon with chalk or the like.<lb/>
But on the wall, they press it while the plaster is still soft <lb/>
by knowing (as I said) how to make <lb/>
paintings in Fresco with an experienced hand;<lb/>
which, in our Countries, is not done.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p047r_6</id>

<ab>
11. Nonetheless, the <i>Florentine</i>, who knew<lb/>
 how to sculpt as well as paint, <lb/>
when he was asked to create his <lb/>
<i>Vatican</i> Last Judgment in Oil,  <lb/>
for according to his account, this manner<lb/>
of painting was the work of Women; <lb/>
while working in Fresco he praised<lb/>
as being an artful, Manly work.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Here is discussed Michelangelo, who called Oil-painting Women’s work and Fresco, Man’s work</ab>
</div>

</root>