<root>
<page>016r</page>

<div>

<id>p016r_1</id>

<ab>
as large as the [finished] work, though with courage,<lb/> 
free and fearless, this I must admonish–<lb/> 
so that you will avoid a manner<lb/> 
of working which is heavy, uncertain,<lb/> 
too stilted, difficult or laborious.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Avoid a heavy style.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p016r_2</id>

<ab>
10. Also, in your cartoon, so as not to err,<lb/> 
you should incorporate much from life,<lb/> 
enhanced and deepened<lb/> 
with watercolor, chalk or charcoal, all commanded<lb/> 
at your choice, and at your will:<lb/> 
but if you wish to give your compositions<lb/> 
pleasingly fine [and] good vigor,<lb/> 
you must take note of various things.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Use details from life in drawing cartoons.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p016r_3</id>

<ab>
11. First you should discover by exploring<lb/> 
the proper foundation in your composition:<lb/> 
when you adroitly fill your scene <lb/> 
on both sides with your bold <lb/> 
foreground figures, buildings, and other staffage,<lb/> 
and keep the center free and open<lb/> 
so as to add as little as possible, <lb/> 
this will achieve success later on.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Fill in the corners well on both sides.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p016r_4</id>

<ab>
12. Our composition should enjoy<lb/> 
a fine character, to our sense of satisfaction, <lb/> 
if we allow a view inside, or a vista<lb/> 
with small background figures, and a distant<lb/> 
landscape into which the eye can plunge.<lb/> 
Therefore in the middle of the foreground<lb/> 
we can have our figures sometimes sit or lie down<lb/> 
so that we can see over them for several miles.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
On allowing a view through, where appropriate.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p016r_5</id>

<ab>
13. But in particular, we will end up with little grace<lb/> 
in our composition if our backgrounds<lb/> 
are other than well executed.<lb/> 
For this purpose the Italians employ us<lb/> 
As foreigners from abroad, since they regard Netherlanders<lb/> 
as bold experts in landscape painting<lb/> 
–if they are to exalt us in anything–<lb/> 
while they surpass us in painting figures.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>If the backgrounds or landscapes are not well executed, the work is disfigured.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p016r_6</id>

<ab>
14.  One should still try in various ways<lb/> 
to compose well, and spend some time<lb/> 
patiently, especially to avoid haste, <lb/> 
arranging all the figures as you must:<lb/> 
like the Italians, who greatly celebrate<lb/> 
composition in various groups,<lb/> 
which their little knots or bands of people, to wit:<lb/> 
here standing, there lying down, and there sitting.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Of composing in various knots [of figures], and leaving some ground in between.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p016r_7</id>

<ab>
15. Here is a battle of terrible skirmishes;<lb/> 
one group should be in the distance, fleeing elsewhere,<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Example of a walking pose, or a weary figure.
</ab>

</div>
</root>