<root>
<page>018r</page>

<div>

<id>p018r_1</id>

<ab>
Ajax, Hyacinth, or Narcissus.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>O<!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p018r_2</id>

<ab>
33. Similarly, the eyes, which love to wander<lb/> 
in all the beauty of Pictura’s court<lb/> 
seek many places enjoy themselves,<lb/> 
wherever their desire for pleasure is guided,<lb/> 
hungering to see more below and above,<lb/> 
like finicky guests, trying everything:<lb/> 
for the Graces delight in <lb/> 
the artistic uses of variety.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>As many various things are well painted, is a delight to see.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p018r_3</id>

<ab>
34. Yet some Histories in particular <lb/> 
ought to be simpler than others,<lb/> 
still others are more skillfully composed:<lb/> 
one should work like a merchant <lb/> 
who artfully displays his goods <lb/> 
on high shelves, at the sides and below;<lb/> 
so one should compose the History with some onlookers,<lb/> 
on hills, trees, or stone steps. <lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On arranging figures high and low.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p018r_4</id>

<ab>
35. Or holding on to columns of the architecture,<lb/> 
as well as others in front, on the ground below.<lb/> 
Further, it gives the History a fine radiance<lb/> 
to include many different faces,<lb/> 
as the noblest part of the body,<lb/> 
as is seen in the manner of the world,<lb/> 
and to create the most pleasing and diverting<lb/> 
presentation; and this shall not do badly.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>On including many faces in the work  Tronien</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p018r_5</id>

<ab>
36.  The noble figures should stand out,<lb/> 
standing tall or sitting raised<lb/> 
above the rest: and those who address them<lb/> 
should humbly show obedience,<lb/> 
in a lower place, and dispirited.<lb/> 
Thus with all our characters: they should be<lb/> 
placed on all sides, to perform <lb/> 
their actions like fine actors. <lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On elevating the noble figures, and making the others downcast.

</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p018r_6</id>

<ab>
37. Thus these figures should perform gracefully while<lb/> 
walking, standing, striding, courting, playing, or dancing;<lb/> 
in fear, in awe, in mourning;<lb/> 
displaying the meaning of the story with their gestures:<lb/> 
in sum, all the expressions of affections <lb/> 
<i>Poses</i>, <i>reflections<, manifestations,<lb/> 
whatever matters to our art, must at the same time<lb/> 
be employed in the History.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>In the History, everything our Art embraces or understands will be employed.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p018r_7</id>

<ab>
38.  The History will have no small ornament, <lb/> 
if one of the figures is turned <lb/> 
toward the people in such a way<lb/> 
that he wishes, with a guiding gesture<lb/> 
compassionately  to explain a sad thing<lb/> 
or something terrible about to happen,<lb/> 
he soon infuses the viewers <i>Gemaals</i><lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>On making a figure who appears to address people and to indicate something unfortunate happening.</ab>

</div>
</root>