<root>
<page>010v</page>

<div>

<id>p010v_1</id>


<ab>
compare a Human Body and a Temple.<lb/>
This agrees well with the word of the Lord<lb/>
when he speaks of destroying the Temple,<lb/>
meaning, by the Temple, his pure Body.<sup><comment>3 John 2: 18-21: The Jews then responded to him, 
“What sign can you show us to prove your authority to do all this?” Jesus answered them, 
“Destroy this temple, and I will raise it again in three days.” They replied, 
“It has taken forty-six years to build this temple, and you are going to raise it in three days?” 
But the temple he had spoken of was his body.></comment></sup> <lb/>
The form of a righteous man’s body <lb/>
is noble, and wondrously composed <lb/>
by Nature with particular art. <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The Human Body compared to a temple with its sections.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p010v_2</id>

<ab>
3. From where the hair begins to grow on the forehead<lb/>
to under the chin, which we call the Face,<lb/>
is the tenth part of the Body’s size <lb/>
measured in length; <lb/>
also the length of the hand, from where <lb/>
it can bend at the very end of the arm<lb/>
to the end of the middle finger,<lb/>
will match the length of the face.<sup><comment>4 This passage is taken directly from Vitruvius, 
<i>De Architectura</i>, Book III, 2-3.
<a href="http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/e/roman/texts/vitruvius/3*.html" target="_blank">Natalis Comes</a>
</comment></sup><lb/>
</ab>
<ab>
<margin>left-middle</margin>A person is ten faces tall, and reaches as wide as he is tall.
	<sup><comment>5 VM uses “Mens,” while Vitruvius’ Latin is “homo.” I have translated as “person” 
	instead of “man.”</comment></sup>
</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p010v_3</id>

<ab>
4. When one measures the size of the whole <lb/>
Head, from crown to chin, one will find <lb/>
an eighth of the Body’s height; and if you stretch a thread<lb/>
behind, from the crown to the base of the neck,<lb/>
you will find an eighth; and from the hairline<lb/>
on the forehead descending to the middle of the chest<lb/>
at the point where it arches the highest, <lb/>
one will find exactly a sixth<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>A Person is eight heads tall.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p010v_4</id>

<ab>
5. When you increase your measure to the crown<lb/>
you will observe a fourth of the Body’s height;<lb/>
if you wish to find the measure of the face,<lb/>
from the hairline to the eyes<lb/>
above the nose and between the eyebrows<lb/>
is to construct a third of the whole Face.<lb/>
The nose is one part, and from the nostrils<lb/>
To the base of the chin is of the same length.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>A Person’s face is three noses long.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p010v_5</id>


<ab>
6. The foot, from where the round part of the heel begins<lb/>
to the end of the second toe, truly, <lb/>
is a sixth of the body’s height;<lb/>
and the cubit–so that we understand,<lb/>
the arm from the elbow joint<lb/>
to the end of the longest finger– <lb/>
will always occupy a fourth of the body’s height.<lb/>
Thus is the construction of the body determined.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>A Person’s foot, at its longest, is a sixth of his height</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>A Person is four cubits tall. The Cubit of the Ancients is six 
palms; each palm is four thumbs long, and there are four palms to a foot. </ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p010v_6</id>


<ab>
7. Now the chest, measured from the beginning of the stomach,<lb/>
just above the navel, to up against<lb/>
the chin, shows the same length. <lb/>
Put the point of a long compass on the navel,<lb/>
When a person is laid out flat, <lb/>
Then let the other point draw a circle,<lb/>
Then you will precisely hit the toes and fingers.<lb/>
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>A Person’s navel is his midpoint. </ab>

</div>
</root>