<root>
<page>042v</page>

<div>

<id>p042v_1</id>


<ab>
(like grain with Wine), as is fitting. <lb/>
For necessity and modesty teach us<lb/>
to cover the Body, and put on clothes,<lb/>
especially here in the North, under the Great Bear,<lb/>
which nowadays hands over our heads.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042v_2</id>

<ab>
2. The Body, wonderfully created, exceeds<lb/>
in honor all kinds of precious linen,<lb/>
thread from silkworms, and clothes of Tyrian purple:<lb/>
and those who are our antipodes,<lb/>
living in the tranquil kingdom of Saturn,<lb/>
unaware of shame, care nothing for clothes.<lb/>
Yet reason, creating an honorable modesty,<lb/>
guides us to a suitably moderate clothing.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The well-made Human Body, more beautiful than all manner of clothing. </ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>In India they go naked, but here shame teaches us to be clothed</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042v_3</id>

<ab>
3. One dresses for one’s own station,<lb/>
that is, according to a person’s esteem: <lb/>
Kings wear purple, ornamented with Crowns,<lb/>
and cheerful Youths are pleased to deck themselves<lb/>
in brilliant, exquisite colors,<lb/>
while maidens will favor white. In these matters,<lb/>
Painters must pay close attention to all,<lb/>
To clothe each thus according to one’s station.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Clothing depends on the person. Colors of clothes according to the nature and age of each.
</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042v_4</id>

<ab>
4. Black, today as in earlier times, signifies mourning,<lb/>
as will be described in due course;<lb/>
it is thus that Widows and Old Men are dressed.<lb/>
Likewise, Shepherds and Boatmen should be given<lb/>
coarsely woven woolen Fabric, <lb/>
in various shades of gray,<lb/>
worn tight around the body, with large folds,<lb/>
and rarely adorned with bright colors.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042v_5</id>
<ab>
5. All that <i>Arachne’s</i> Art offers in abundance,<lb/>
we must observe with diligent attention,<lb/>
starting with Cloth that weavers roll
from the rough warp, and others: wools<lb/>
velvets, serges, silks, how each creates folds <lb/>
according to its nature, taking care not to paint <lb/>
ropes, sails, or intestines, but real Cloth,<lb/>
appearing flat, hanging or rumpled.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Various Cloths; observing different folds or creases.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Beginning with the Cloth which Weavers roll.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042v_6</id>


<ab>
6. Coarse Linen makes straight folds <lb/>
with sharp corners, like wet Paper.<lb/>
One sees jagged crumpling of this sort<lb/>
quite often in <i>Dürer’s</i> fabric;<lb/>
though painting of the fine rumpled cloth <lb/>
worn, say, by children of the Madonna,<lb/>
one can find no better example<lb/>
than those by <i>Mabuse</i>, if truth be told.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Creases in coarse linen.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example of Dürer’s cloth.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example of Mabuse’s fine linens.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p042v_7</id>


7. But no matter which fold of Cloth is praised<lb/>
above others, this requires attention: <lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

</root>