<root>
<page>048v</page>

<div>

<id>p048v_1</id>


<ab>
could not produce anything better<lb/>
than a board with ugly gouges.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048v_2</id>

<ab>
24. They believed they were [working] well practiced<lb/>
and deceived themselves, being quite wrong.<lb/>
Because they thought that his works were done <lb/>
without effort, though the extreme powers<lb/>
of Art were achieved with difficulty.<lb/>
 For one sees his pictures repainted<lb/>
and covered with several layers of colors.<lb/>
They required much more effort than one would think.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Many intend to imitate Titian and become lost.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048v_3</id>

<ab>
25. But this manner of working, from<lb/>
the good judgment and intelligence of Titian, <lb/>
is deemed especially beautiful and graceful.<lb/>
For (says <i>Vasari</i>) the labor is hidden <lb/>
beneath great Art, and that such Painting<lb/>
makes one almost believe that it is alive,<lb/>
and as I have said, that his works appear<lb/>
easy, though they were made with toil.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Titian’s works, which were made with labor, appear to have been made without it.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048v_4</id>

<ab>
26. Here, O noble scholars of painting, <lb/>
I have wished to describe and show you<lb/>
two different manners, both sound,<lb/>
so that you might direct your thoughts with pleasure<lb/>
toward the one which most quickens your spirit.<lb/>
But I should advise you to at first to concern yourself,<lb/>
And become accustomed, with a zealous mind,<lb/>
To a clean manner, beginning with neatness.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Of two manners to choose from, it is advised to grow accustomed to neatness at first.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048v_5</id>

<ab>
27. Take courage, with a cheerful heart,<lb/>
and strengthen your spirit with steely patience:<lb/>
paint rough or smooth, and always avoid<lb/>
carving your work with sharp-edged highlights–<lb/>
as was done in earlier times, <lb/>
and was not good to look at–<lb/>
rather, use the sound manner discovered at the end,<lb/>
for the work of our Forebears did not have roundness.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Taking courage, and however one paints, avoiding sharp-edged highlights, for they will not have the effect of roundness.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048v_6</id>

<ab>
28. but a sharp-edged painting will look too flat.<lb/>
Thus you should strive for the best manner.<lb/>
For example, you must determine the size of a Column<lb/>
And divide its thickness into three. <lb/>
Draw two points  at equal distances between the contour lines,<lb/>
and on the first point create your brightest highlight, <lb/>
and  at the second point, your deepest shadow,<lb/>
with its width correct.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The old modern pictures looked very flat. </ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The manner of highlighting and shadowing. Example of a Column.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p048v_7</id>

<ab>
29. Lay down your ground color between these two areas.<lb/>
From the edge of the highlight, darken gradually;<lb/>
the other edge prefers to receive a reflection.<lb/>
Now regarding colors: do not freeze blush color, <lb/>
Or make it so cold, that is, empurpled. <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On ground color, or mezza tinta.</ab>

</div>

</root>