<root>
<page>036r</page>

<div>

<id>p036r_1</id>

<ab>
that is: a beginning in front, all the planes<lb/>
should be fixed and bound with one another,<lb/>
just as we see, in Neptune’s realm,<lb/>
the waves all rolling with one another.<lb/>
So, the planes should merge sinuously together, <lb/>
not piled up one behind the other.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On connecting the planes to one another.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p036r_2</id>

<ab>
21. If we link our planes together like this,<lb/>
and so allow one to glide into another <lb/>
slithering like a twisting adder.<lb/>
Do not abandon fading into the distance,<lb/>
for the background regions must be sound.<lb/>
We should avoid having Mountains, Hills, Dikes<lb/>
in a strong dark clash against soft light;<lb/>
rather, the benefit comes with half color.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>To make the planes hang together properly, the Landscape should fade well into the distance. </ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Not placing dark planes or others against the light.  </ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p036r_3</id>

<ab>
22. One should not place Houses in the foreground,<lb/>
unless wishing to tell a story <lb/>
constructed from half Landscape and half figures;<lb/>
One should work according to the subject, but otherwise avoid<lb/>
a heavy composition, which smothers the space.<lb/>
Yet without too much abundance, let the grounds<lb/>
As is fitting, bloom with some beautiful greenery.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Large houses will be unbecoming in the foreground, though some beautiful greenery will, only not too abundant.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p036r_4</id>

<ab>
23. We should imitate, in a wise and informed manner, <lb/>
great variety, in colors as in life,<lb/>
for it offers a great and laudable beauty.<lb/>
Yet in this regard we must avoid <lb/>
imprudently adding Cities, Houses, Mountains, <lb/>
or other objects too abundantly.<lb/>
Indeed, this hinders the enjoyment of a balanced composition,<lb/>
even if it is in the distance.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Too many Mountains, Cities, Houses or background elements are unsightly. </ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p036r_5</id>

<ab>
24.  The Italians painting Landscapes<lb/>
are few but artful, almost without peer,<lb/>
and in large part show views<lb/>
into a single perspective along with very sturdy<lb/>
Planes and Cities–indeed, whatever they display.<lb/>
Above <i>Tintoretto</i> is the magnificent <lb/>
<i>Titian</i>, whose woodcut will teach us <lb/>
what we see from that Painter of Brescia.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The Italians, few in number but excellent Landscapists, most often create a single perspective view, and are excellent at sturdy grounds and buildings.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p036r_6</id>

<ab>
25. In regard to these, I wish to boast proudly<lb/>
of the well-colored and ingenious compositions<lb/>
in the paintings and prints of Bruegel.<lb/>
Here, for example in the peaked rocky Alps,<lb/>
he teaches us to depict views<lb/>
deep into a dizzying ravine,<lb/>
steep crags and cloud-kissing Pine trees,<lb/>
Distant vistas, and rushing streams.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The Landscapes and prints of Bruegel as examples.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p036r_7</id>

<ab>
26. From lofty, sparse hills, leave off<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Of different mountains and valleys, with their colors.</ab>

</div>

</root>