<root>
<page>054v</page>

<div>

<id>p054v_1</id>


<ab>
24. Just as in coats of arms, clear, glowing Gold <lb/>
can indicate nobility and majesty,<lb/>
Silver, purity and merciful justice; <lb/>
Red meaning magnificence, courage and valor;<lb/>
Blue, faithfulness, and the practice of knowledge;<lb/>
Green, beauty, goodness and joy; and to continue,<lb/>
Purple, abundance, the favor of Gods and Men;<lb/>
Black, humility and the sadness dwelling in the heart.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Meanings of the seven Colors in heraldry.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p054v_2</id>

<ab>
25.  Two metals, Silver and Gold by name,<lb/>
could not exist in noble coats of arms<lb/>
by themselves; and likewise, colors<lb/>
do not belong together without metals.<lb/>
Among the Planets, Gold <lb/>
is compared to the Sun; by the moon<lb/>
we understand Silver; and <i>Mars</i> with red,<lb/>
<i>Mercury</i>, messenger of the Gods, with Purple.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Fixed order in heraldry, or the Coats of Arms of Nobles. </ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The seven colors are like the seven Planets, which one should dress in its appropriate color</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054v_3</id>

<ab>
26. We liken <i>Jupiter</i> to Blue, <i>Venus</i> to green,<lb/>
melancholy <i>Saturn</i> with Black.<lb/>
In the same manner, one can compare<lb/>
with colors the days of the week,<lb/>
beginning with Sunday; <lb/>
also the seven Virtues, without failing:<lb/>
Faith with Gold; Silver is kindly Hope;<lb/>
And ardent Love or Charity is Red.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Also with the days of the week.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The seven Virtues are like the colors.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054v_4</id>

<ab>
27. <i>Justice</i> with the sky’s exquisite Blue;<lb/>
Green is Strength, to persevere with dignity;<lb/>
and Black, Wisdom or Prudence, modest in practice,<lb/>
and two colors, whose names are lost,<lb/>
mingled into one: Violet flesh-color, <lb/>
which is like Temperance, moderate in its nature.<lb/>
One can also compare liken these Colors to<lb/>
the seven ages of human life.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054v_5</id>

<ab>
28. A child up to seven years old after birth<lb/>
is Silver or white, innocent and charming;<lb/>
Blue is an inexperienced Youth up to fifteen years;<lb/>
Gold-yellow, the Young man up to twenty years;<lb/>
Green is a Young man up to thirty.<lb/>
Red, a valiant Man up to fifty;<lb/>
Purple is to an elder up to seventy;<lb/>
Black, in mourning, is reserved for death.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The seven Ages of Man’s life, compared to the colors.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p054v_6</id>

<ab>
29.  Four types, or human temperaments,<lb/>
can also compare to four colors, first Sanguine, <lb/>
full of blood, with Red; quick-tempered Choleric<lb/>
with Blue; and with White, the Phlegmatic,<lb/>
slimy and phlegm-filled in all seasons;<lb/>
Black corresponds with the sad face of melancholy.<lb/>
Further, if we wish to identify the Elements, <lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Four colors compared to the four human Temperaments, and four elements.</ab>

</div>

</root>