<root>
<page>045r</page>

<div>

<id>p045r_1</id>

<ab>
who helped the son of Pythius with his work:<lb/>
our Idea here must show its power.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Pythius was the Father of Apelles. Idea, imagination, or thought.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045r_2</id>

<ab>
31. I have already seen how gracefully<lb/>
the gowns and veils of <i>Nymphs</i> waft like sails,<lb/>
mostly in one direction, sometimes turning<lb/>
here and there with the wind; and how <lb/>
gently rippling are the shifts and veils <lb/>
of the wanton <i>Bacchantes</i>, running lustily<lb/>
with torches up and down the steep hills, <lb/>
and <i>Diana’s</i> maidens hunting in the wilds.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The floating veils and linens of the Nymphs.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045r_3</id>

<ab>
32. Now, who cannot see the Bull bathing in the Sea,<lb/>
and the maiden’s gown moving like a sail?<lb/>
Who would deny our reading <lb/>
the inventive <i>Exile</i>? How fearful he paints<lb/>
the young abducted girl! Who could tire of<lb/>
the veils and ribbons along her Marble throat, <lb/>
with her golden hair, all floating in the air?<lb/>
It is right that our Brush listens to such writing.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The Example of Europa, described by Ovid.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The Painter’s brush listens to the Poet’s pen.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p045r_4</id>

<ab>
33. I will leave you to take care of<lb/>
what concerns us further in these matters:<lb/>
to make other forms of clothing,<lb/>
various embroideries, cloth of gold,<lb/>
and also multicolored Damask, with figures.<lb/>
Pay attention to everything, so as to make no error<lb/>
When naturally representing a large elaborate fabric; <lb/>
for that, you must also arrange the colors.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Figured Fabrics and Damasks.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p045r_5</id>

<ab>
<b>End of Cloth, or Drapery.</b>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p045r_6</id>

<ab>
<b>XI. On the Variation or Combining of Colors.<lb/>
The Eleventh Chapter.</b>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p045r_7</id>

<ab>
1. You, Scholars of Art which begins in Nature,<lb/>
will wish to lend your avid ears here.<lb/>
I shall tell you in what manner<lb/>
to arrange your colors properly<lb/>
so as to vary them well, according to correct intention;<lb/>
which ones (without mixing) <lb/>
are close to each other and willingly go together<lb/>
when you start making Draperies<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Colors which are pleased to go together.</ab>
</div>

</root>