<root>
<page>043v</page>

<div>

<id>p043v_1</id>


<ab>
there is no need to wrinkle the Cloth too much<lb/>
with confused and laborious folds,<lb/>
as if all were digested and broken.<lb/>
In this matter our Predecessors made <lb/>
many unskilled errors, particularly <i>Aldegraver</i>,<lb/>
who wrongly misused excessive folds–<lb/>
that is, the manner which is called “confusing<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Avoid a confusion of folds.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example: Aldegrever used broken folds in an exaggerated manner.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p043v_2</id>

<ab>
14. But Dürer’s Fabric, especially the last<lb/>
one sees in his prints, with such <lb/>
magnificently large flat areas, leaving<lb/>
the rest in deep shadow, as his best<lb/>
<i>Mary</i> figures show, is splendid and instructive.<lb/>
It would be a great misdeed, and an ignoble thing,<lb/>
to accuse such a Man of “confusion.”<lb/>
The nature of Art will never tolerate it.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example: cloth with flat areas by Albrecht Dürer.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p043v_3</id>

<ab>
15. The pride of the <i>Batavians</i> and of the <i>Germans</i>,<lb/>
<i>Lucas</i>, and <i>Albrecht</i>, on whom the Chorus of <i>Muses</i><lb/>
has showered all its gifts, have granted the Italians<lb/>
great profit and benefit with their prints, <lb/>
and thus, their draperies. Yes, perhaps <lb/>
even more than one could think,<lb/>
because, with skill and intelligence,<lb/>
they knew how to vary a little.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Lucas and Albrecht’s prints, Examples.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p043v_4</id>

<ab>
16. In <i>Lucas’s</i> cloth one finds many fine ruffles.<lb/>
In the <i>Magdalen</i>, <i>Mordecai</i>, and <i>The Temptation of Christ</i> <lb/>
one sees him execute the movement <lb/>
of small folds with his skilled burin. <lb/>
Who could pour out this flow with greater delicacy?<lb/>
Now Youths, like Bees, you would do well<lb/>
to suck from these Roses the dripping nectar <lb/>
and sweet honey, unusually useful.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p043v_5</id>
<ab>
17. Without faltering, make a flowing Cloth, <lb/>
rich and unbound, particularly for Women;<lb/>
it would not be easy to reproach you.<lb/>
Rather than making it too short, you should let it trail.<lb/>
And like the branches adorning the trees,<lb/>
make the edges and hems ripple naturally<lb/>
when hanging or spreading, <lb/>
but avoid making crooked corners.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The flowing Cloth of Women.</ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>The edges rippling naturally. </ab>
<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Avoiding crooked corners.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p043v_6</id>

<ab>
18. Now concerning silks and various sheens,<lb/>
the <i>Venetians</i> are in general highly praised;<lb/>
they will serve as a good Example.<lb/>
They know how to work with colors,<lb/>
and arrange them so that the highlights <lb/>
seem to protrude: but one must always<lb/>
add to shining silks such highlights<lb/>
as the Adjacent colors can best support<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example: Venetian Painters’ beautiful silks and sheens, or changeable silks.</ab>

</div>

</root>