<root>
<page>013r</page>

<div>

<id>p013r_1</id>

<ab>
of how the Giants fell,<lb/>
defeated by the fearsome thunder.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p013r_2</id>

<ab>
16. His playing was perceived as far sweeter<lb/>
at another time, when he sang<lb/>
of young maidens who come to grief,<lb/>
driven by foolish love.<lb/>
Notice how we have leapt into this tale, <lb/>
to show that one is sometimes forced<lb/>
to make such changes, according to<lb/>
the style and action of our subject.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p013r_3</id>

<ab>
17. Similarly, when one makes standing figures<lb/>
who are wielding stakes or pulling ropes,<lb/>
the feet and hands must extend on the same side,<lb/>
as well as the arms and legs that stretch together <lb/>
in the direction that the action demands.<lb/>
But one must especially avoid covering<lb/>
the naked Body with the arms, so that<lb/>
if possible it is unencumbered by all limbs.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On depicting figures in action, positioning the limbs according to their activity. </ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On not hiding the beauty of the body, and never obstructing its contours.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p013r_4</id>

<ab>
18. Thus we must further (according to our knowledge)<lb/>
consider an improperly done figure,<lb/>
as when a figure is sitting<lb/>
with the feet turned out sideways<lb/>
and the knees bent inward towards one another.<lb/>
This would not be praised; rather, it would be much better<lb/>
to let the knees bend outward<lb/>
and the heels inward, to enjoy a proper appearance.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
How the knees of a seated figure should and should not bend. 
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p013r_5</id>

<ab>
19. Indeed, making the feet of a woman<lb/>
too far apart when lying or standing,<lb/>
especially when standing, is to be untrue<lb/>
to the correct manner, which demands that<lb/>
the feet be close together, for the sake of decorum.<lb/>
Then at times, one must also avoid inappropriate <lb/>
foreshortening of faces and so forth, <lb/>
since too much of this would lack grace.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>How the legs and feet of a female figure should be placed.</ab>
<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Too much foreshortening is not praiseworthy.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p013r_6</id>

<ab>
20.  Furthermore, many renowned painters (like the lame)<lb/>
wander on a curious wrong path,<lb/>
that is: (if they will not blame me, but thank me)<lb/>
they lift and raise the shoulder highest<lb/>
over the hip which they allow to swing out,<lb/>
while it should always drop lower over the hip which swings out. <lb/>
For this is the essence of art, <lb/>
whether the figure is sitting, lying or standing. <lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
How a figure should move. 
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p013r_7</id>

<ab>
21. Further, there is another mark of folly,<lb/>
when one allows the arm of the lower shoulder,<lb/>
where the body swings out, to reach upward.<lb/>
This will not enhance the figure’s beauty,<lb/>
Even if it were employed for twice as long.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Likewise, the arm which reaches upward must be on the opposite side of the swung hip. 
</ab>

</div>
</root>