<root>
<page>001r</page>

<div>
<id>p001r_0</id>

<ab><b>
CHAPTER I:	EXHORTATION, OR LECTURE, TO RISING YOUNG PAINTERS<lb/>
</b></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p001r_1</id>

<ab>1. O Hebe's offspring, Genius's students,<sup><comment>1 Hebe, the Greek goddess of youth; 
	her “offspring” would be children who had reached puberty, around 12 to 15 years old - the 
	standard age for starting an apprenticeship. Genius is allegorized in the Renaissance as 
	the force of human struggle and ambition; see Miedema 355.</comment></sup><lb/> 
who instead of writing, <lb/> 
blotted all over your paper and filled it<lb/> 
with little People, Ships, and various animals<lb/> 
so that you scarcely left a space empty:<sup><comment>2 The trope of drawing small figures at a very young age, as a sign of an emerging painter, was used by Vasari in his description of Cimabue. I, 83. Van Mander in turn described several artists this way in his <i>Lives</i>..</comment></sup>  <lb/> 
It seems that Nature wished to drive you <lb/> 
to become a painter, such that your Parents <lb/> 
assume the burden of bringing you there.<lb/> 
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Parents easily say that they want to make their children Painters, but it is neither their task, nor within their power. 
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p001r_2</id>

<ab>2. By general judgment you were chosen<lb/> 
to be a Painter. The word is easy to speak, <lb/> 
but look: between Painter and Painter<lb/> 
lies a great mountain, rising so high <lb/> 
that many must leave the journey stalled.<lb/> 
This does not concern months or weeks; <lb/> 
rather, you will need whole years<lb/> 
before you taste any benefit.<lb/> 
 
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
Between painter and painter lies a great mountain.
</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p001r_3</id>

<ab>3.  It would not be good if one pushed you to this.	<lb/> 
This Art is itself attractive enough at the start, <lb/> 
easy to grasp, at everyone's command. <lb/> 
But let each make sure to avoid the fate of <lb/> 
the foolish gnat, who, delighting in the shine <lb/> 
 </ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>
<!--Nothing in the margin -->
</ab>

</div>
</root>