<root>
<page>005v</page>

<div>

<id>p005v_1</id>

<ab>
another beginning with a short vowel, 
as can be found in the syllables of the line, thereby ignoring assimilation, especially if it 
suits them: as, for example, one might say, “<i>de achste</i>, <i>de elfste</i>, <i>de ander</i>, <i>geacht</i>, and 
suchlike. But if one says <i>te eer</i>, <i>de eerste</i>, <i>te hebben</i>,  and so forth, where a short vowel 
precedes a long double one, I think no assimilation should follow at all;  also, the aspirant h 
next to the vowel should have the same value as the second vowel. <lb/>
 
Now, I would like to see a general conformity of gender, number, and similar 
elements, such as those used by the French and other nations. For they address a Man as 
<i>Seigneur</i>, and <i>Signor</i>, while we say <i>Heer</i>, and an elder man<i> Heere</i>, <i>Siel</i>, and <i>Siele</i>, <i>Eeer</i>, and 
<i>Eere</i> and so on, changing them to suit us in syllable or rhyme.  This matter, and more, 
will be resolved slowly, for I find many faults, (from which I cannot boast I am free) 
which should be improved.  I leave it and trust to those experts who work on this. <lb/>
 
I turn now to my young Painters, whom I intend to teach to paint, not to write 
poetry. Therefore I say that, if there are competent and perspicacious young minds 
attracted by learning our art of painting–and whose souls, when they were joined to the 
body as well as to the life force, descended from the heights and passed at the right 
moment by the spheres of the stars that bestow intelligence; or in their first breath 
they breathe in from these beneficial bodies a strong inclination to be skilled in Painting, to 
speak in a scientific manner–these spirits will be able to accept with gratitude what I offer 
them so willingly, and be attentive, with awakened intelligence, to all the instructive 
subjects that I propose to them in my foundation of the Art of Painting, or in the entire 
Painter’s Book. I hope that the advantage or profit is not small for them. <lb/>
 
To this end, I shall gladly speak to them with a willing heart and give them 
courage. Just as the commanders of ancient Rome observed from the spear-shaking of 
their warriors that their boldness was brought to life by eloquent oration: so I hope that 
they will gather fearlessly and attack first the most important element of the Arts, namely, 
to learn to pose a Human figure. Then, they become familiar with all the other aspects of 
Art, or, if Nature and the Spirit do not allow it, to excel in with at least one aspect.  For it 
does not happen every day, that by oneself one can be instructed, learn and comprehend, 
or achieve excellence, in everything.<lb/>
 
This is how it happened in our Art, since old or Ancient times: that one was more 
competent in one area, and another was a better Master in another area, as we shall see in 
their biographies. For <i>Apollodorus</i> concentrated in particular on beauty. <i>Zeuxis</i> made heads 
which were too large but was a fine painter of Fruit. <i>Eumarus</i> was skilled at making 
everything from life. <i>Protogenes</i> could only paint ships. <i>Apelles</i> did everything with grace.  
<i>Parrhasius</i> was good at contour drawing. <i>Demon</i>, full of invention; <i>Tymanthes</i>, intelligence: 
in his work there was always a hidden idea or meaning. <i>Pamphilus</i> was learned; 
<i>Nicomachus</i>, swift. <i>Athenion</i>, profound.<i> Nicophanes</i>, neat and clean; <i>Amulius</i>, good at 
colors. <i>Pausias</i>, skilled
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in the margin --></ab>
</div>
</root>