<root>
<page>005r</page>

<div>
<id>p005r_1</id>

<ab>
I might well have trespassed in this. Foreign words I have not completely 
avoided, since sometimes in our profession we use words which would otherwise sound 
incorrect. <lb/>

Perhaps it might be pleasing to those who know about Poetry if I had composed 
my poem in French meter; but this would have been too difficult for me, and too obscure 
for Young people to understand. I concede that one could compose something good with 
Alexandrines, in the Gallic manner, but it requires great concentration and time to fill it 
with fine material while still flowing. I also consider it very fine and melodious to make 
the second syllable strong or long, and the first one short, such as that used first in our 
language by the great Poet Heer <i>Jan van Hout</i>, Pensionary of the city of Leiden, who in 
his youth observed this in <i>Petrarch</i>, <i>Ronsard</i>, and others, and imitated them.<lb/>
 
As I begin to discuss the art of Poetry, I wish to state in brief (if appropriate 
here) my feelings and desires about this, that is, about the French style and meter up 
and coming with us, offering some examples of good and bad verse.  First, from the 
Community of ten and eleven syllables, this line of eleven, with its feminine or 
falling rhyme, sounds good to me:<lb/>
 
<blockquote>
<i>Schoon jonghe Ieught, Meestersse van mijn leven.</i><lb/>
[beautiful young maid, Mistress of my life]<lb/>
</blockquote>
 
Good, because within the first four syllables before the caesura is one 
complete idea, and descriptive words are next to its word of substance, which 
in Latin is called <i>Adiectivum</i> next to the <i>Substantivum</i>. Furthermore, because 
the latter part of the line contains a complete meaning on its own, without 
having to rely on the next part. <lb/>
 
The following, of ten syllables, with a standing rhyme, is not so good:<lb/>
 
<blockquote>
	<i>Een Man die wel ervaren is ter Zee.</i><lb/>
	[A Man well experienced at Sea]<lb/>
</blockquote>
Because the part before the caesura at wel must rely on the second. <lb/>

Now, concerning the six-foot Alexandrines, of twelve and thirteen syllables, which have a caesura on the sixth, I think this line of thirteen is good: <lb/>

<blockquote>
	<i>In Gods gheplanten Hof, in't lustigh Ooftigh Eden.</i><lb/>
	[In the Garden planted by God, in the lovely Eden of the East]<lb/>
</blockquote>
Because the part before the caesura, and the entirety, contain a full, complete idea. <lb/>
 
This one, of twelve, is quite poor, or bad:<lb/>
 
<blockquote>
<i>Daerom ick bidd' u, wilt noch lijdtsaem wesen: want.</i><lb/>
[I implore you, be patient still: for]<lb/>
</blockquote>
Because the first part before the caesura relies on <i>noch lijdtsaem wesen</i>; also because the 
whole line is neither completed nor comprehensible; and because want must rely on the 
following line. Therefore <i>want</i>, and <i>maer</i>, and suchlike should not stand before the 
caesura or pause, nor rhyme at the end of the line, if one wishes to make a good poem.
 
Furthermore, the last line, except for the word <i>lijdsaem</i>, contains nothing other than 
common everyday talk, which Alexandrines easily lend themselves to because of their 
length, if they are not governed by judgment. But the previous lines of thirteen is full of 
fine substantive words and descriptive words, free of everyday talk. I consider these 
examples, and few words, enough to make my opinion known. <lb/>
 
However, there are some more things used by our Netherlandish Poets which 
displease me and cannot be justified.  Not paying attention to the assimilation of vowels, 
they place a word ending in a short vowel next to 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin -->.</ab>

</div>
</root>