<root>
<page>004r</page>

<div>
<id>p004r_0</id>

<ab>
<b>Preface to the Foundation of the Noble Liberal Art of Painting.</b>
</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p004r_1</id>

<ab>
The greatly diverting and noble art of Painting, which generates intelligence, 
natural Nurse of all worthy Arts and sciences (as those sufficiently Learned in letters are 
aware) was always held in great esteem by most Gentlemen and highly learned men. 
Indeed, the wise ancient Greeks held such respect for her that in the time of the artful 
Painter <i>Pamphilus</i>, they gave her the same level or position of honor as the other liberal 
Arts. <lb/>

But whether, either in or through this association, our excellent art of Painting has 
not, by her worthy presence, by her appearance, brings more honor to the other arts than 
she has received by the dignity of their company: I prefer to keep my feelings to myself, 
so as not to be rebuked with stormy looks, to be thought of unfavorably, or to cause much 
confusion. Nonetheless it cannot be denied that, if she is worthy of her place among the 
others, from which she has never been excluded by anyone, then she may well and 
properly be called liberal. <lb/> 

Her nobility and high worth have been confirmed by many great monuments and 
deeds in antiquity. First, the other liberal Arts have never been esteemed anywhere to the 
point where it is forbidden to teach them to common folk: this was the case with the art of 
Painting, which no one except those of Noble birth were permitted to learn. Furthermore, 
the law of the Roman Emperor Justinian states that a 
painted board, or panel, is the property of the artful Painter, and follows him, if he has 
painted on it. On the other hand, the Parchment or Paper does not come into the 
possession of a clever writer even if he has written on it with Letters of gold; it continues 
to belong to the owner.<lb/>

We must also note what beautiful and magnificent trophies adorn our <i>Pictura</i>. 
Straightaway one sees here the worldly scepter of the great <i>Alexander</i> united with 
<i>Apelles’</i> Brush, bound together and hanging: there, the beautiful <i>Campaspe</i> is presented 
to the Painter. Elsewhere, the gold of the Lydian King <i>Candaules</i> is weighed against the 
paintings of <i>Bularchus</i>; here the wealth of Cities, against the paintings of <i>Apelles</i>, <i>Echin</i>, 
<i>Melanthys</i>, and <i>Nicomachus</i>. There, against a painting in four colors by <i>Apelles</i>, stands a 
hundredweight of gold, and elsewhere lie eighty talents’ worth of gold for a <i>Medea and 
Ajax</i>, painted by <i>Timomachus</i><sup><comment>1 None of these works survive; they, and the works referred 
to below, are known chiefly through Pliny the Elder</comment></sup>. <lb/>

Still further off lie a hundred Talents for a painting by the artful <i>Aristides</i> of 
<i>Thebes</i>, bought at an auction; and further, King <i>Attalus</i>, distressed because a painted 
<i>Bacchus</i> was refused and denied to him in exchange for six thousand Sesterces.  Behold, 
still more astonishing: there is an unfinished canvas, barely drawn on by <i>Apelles</i> and 
<i>Protogenes</i>, which is more highly valued than all the treasures in the Palace of <i>Caesar</i>. It 
is also glorious, and praiseworthy, that three Cities, <i>Rhodes</i>, <i>Ciconia</i>,  and <i>Syracuse</i>, 
thank our Art with great respect, that she was not bloodily destroyed through cruel<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><i>Institutes</i> Book 2, paragraph 27<sup><comment>4 Note here on Justinian and the Institutes.</comment></sup>.</ab>

</div>
</root>