<root>
<page>023r</page>

<div>

<id>p023r_1</id>

<ab>
These and suchlike are known as the Emotions.<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>O<!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p023r_2</id>

<ab>
3. <i>Aristides</i> of Thebes first began to express<lb/>
these things (which the Greeks called <i>Ethe</i>)<lb/>
in color, seeking to pick in the garden of Art <lb/>
beautiful new Flowers which smell lovely;<lb/>
About his wounded wife and her sickness,<lb/>
And the growth of his renown,<lb/>
We will soon attend to this subject.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Aristides, the first to depict the Emotions.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p023r_3</id>

<ab>
4. These emotions are not as ready or easy<lb/>
to express as they are declared,<lb/>
first with the parts of the face,<lb/>
ten or more different views,<lb/>
as, one forehead, two eyes, and above them<lb/>
two eyebrows, and beneath them <lb/>
two cheeks, and in between, nose and chin<lb/>
and two-lipped mouth, and what is inside.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>The parts of the face with which the emotions are expressed.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p023r_4</id>

<ab>
5.  Here the Painter must pay tireless attention<lb/>
to examining the natural essence,<lb/>
in order to arrange these parts<lb/>
in relation to one another, so that they reveal<lb/>
the things that move the heart,<lb/>
to perform them with the body’s gestures:<lb/>
Everything that the emotions can bring about,  <lb/>
Nature reveals more than one can describe.<lb/>

</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Nature reveals the Emotions.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p023r_5</id>

<ab>
6. Yet it would be improper for us to deviate from<lb/>
some ways, rules and orders<lb/>
in order to depict these things well,<lb/>
so that all our characters play<lb/>
according to the <i>Histrionic</i> Art, and perform<lb/>
such gestures as would <lb/>
appear on a <i>Stage</i>, be it in Comedy <lb/>
with joy, or in sorrowful Tragedy.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p023r_6</id>

<ab>
7. Now let us first in our work <lb/>
build a portrayal of the emotion of Love <lb/> 
between Men and Women according to our kind,<lb/>
with an affectionate smiling gaze,<lb/>
with embracing, and encircling arms,<lb/>
and heads inclining toward <lb/>
one another as if overflowing with Love,<lb/>
with rights hands clasped.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>On portraying the emotion of Love.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p023r_7</id>

<ab>
8. Also between lovers the greatness of Love<lb/>
can be difficult to feign, yet easy to betray,<lb/>
through painful shame and exposure of the heart,<lb/>
spoiling the face with a rosy redness.<lb/>
And here we wish to add the Example,<lb/>
(to confirm and fulfill this argument)<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>An example of a History of Antiochus and his Stepmother <i>Stratonice</i>.</ab>

</div>

</root>