<root>
<page>020v</page>

<div>

<id>p020v_1</id>


<ab>
And it surprises me greatly that such Gentlemen<lb/> 
who perhaps never learned to paint<lb/> 
know how to write so picturesquely (schilderachtig)<lb/> 
about our clever secrets,<lb/> 
that I think we should content ourselves <lb/> 
with this example of how one can make additions.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>On the Veil which I have discussed in the chapter on Drawing, on abundant and simple Histories.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p020v_2</id>

<ab>
63.  Further, it is well known that on the World’s stage<lb/> 
There are all kinds of players:<lb/> 
here one sees the King disputing<lb/> 
over Crown and Scepter; elsewhere on stage<lb/> 
young lovers in foolish quarrels;<lb/> 
here Farmers slaughtering Pigs,<lb/> 
there, coarse Peasant Women frolicking and jumping;<lb/> 
over there, Goddesses arrayed in revelry.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p020v_3</id>

<ab>
64. This I believe, that from the marvelously many colors,<lb/> 
forms and essences, all the gestures<lb/> 
employed in the earthly theater, <lb/> 
of vain pleasures and wretched sorrows,<lb/> 
and from all that is available to the Painter,<lb/> 
so he finds enough material to his advantage<lb/> 
to construct perfect compositions<lb/> 
based on the History he has at hand.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p020v_4</id>

<ab>
65. Further, one can amplify simple Histories <lb/> 
even more, in various ways.<lb/> 
For example, in choosing to amplify<lb/> 
the simple Sacrifice of Abraham,<lb/> 
one might embellish it with symbolic figures<lb/> 
–that is, Faith, Hope, and Charity–<lb/> 
so that each of these would lend a helping hand<lb/> 
to aid in the Sacrifice.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>How one may amplify simple Histories even further, be they devotional or otherwise. As an example, the History of the sacrifice of Abraham.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p020v_5</id>


<ab>
66.  Faith might hold Isaac, bound by force,<lb/> 
by the rope; as Abraham stretches out<lb/> 
his hand, Hope offers the knife;<lb/> 
for he hopes to see him again<lb/> 
since God can awaken the dead;<lb/> 
and through Faith he brings him back to that place,<lb/> 
Charity and her children take charge of the fire,<lb/> 
For it burned with fiery coals.<lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Hebrews, 11.19. </ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p020v_6</id>


<ab>
67.  A further example here is the annunciation of Zuccaro,<lb/> 
amplified with Angels and Prophets, <lb/> 
and in the <i>Life</i> of <i>Rosso</i> written by <i>Vasari</i>,<lb/> 
we read of a Madonna<lb/> 
with a serpent trampled under her feet,<lb/> 
and also our first Parents sitting in bondage<lb/> 
at the tree of sins, and she withdraws the sin,<lb/> 
represented by an apple, from their mouths.<lb/> 
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin>Example, the annunciation by Zuccaro, and a Madonna by Rosso, which follows elsewhere in his biography.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p020v_7</id>


<ab>
68. And as a sign that she was clad<lb/>  
</ab>	

<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>
</root>