<root>
<page>029r</page>

<div>

<id>p029r_1</id>

<ab>
Dus Ionghers laet sulcx van u oock gheschieden, 
Want boven t'onderwijs, dat u mocht binnen
Mijn schrijven eenich voordeel doen ghewinnen,
Soo wijs' ick u te volghen de patroonen,
Die welck <i>Eupompus Lisippum</i> ginck toonen.
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Plin. lib. 34. cap. 8.</ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p029r_2</id>

<ab>
<b>Eynde der Affecten.</b>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p029r_3</id>

<ab>
<b>On Reflection, Radiance, Gloss or Luster. <lb/>
The Seventh Chapter.</b>

</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p029r_4</id>

<ab>
1. Speaking of reflection or luster,<lb/>
we must begin with the radiance of the Sun.<lb/>
for one sees its light, stand out above all;<lb/>
all stars would lack clarity<lb/>
without the reflection of the sun,<lb/>
which bestows on the sky its beautiful aspect.<lb/> 
It is the World’s Soul in the midst of the Planets; <lb/>
we should not forget it in our purposes.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Plin. Book. II. Chap. 6.</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p029r_5</id>

<ab>
2. When night, with its black sails of dark omens,<lb/>
needs to retreat from the field,<lb/>
and unveils once again beautiful things <lb/>
in all places on the Face of the earth, <lb/>
then one can see in the shadowy clouds<lb/>
a Radiance, or luster,<lb/>
as the Sun comes to bring joy with the day<lb/>
and spreads the Light with many colors.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>On Dawn</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p029r_6</id>

<ab>
3. It is a delight for heart and mind <lb/>
in the dawn, before one sees appearing<lb/>
the principal light of the Earth with golden rays,<lb/>
to see the azure fields of the Orient<lb/>
sown with red Roses and purple Flowers;<lb/>
How can one find a more beautiful Reflection,<lb/>
which many Poets in earlier times<lb/>
have described with painterly art?<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Aurora is the redness both of morning and evening.</ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p029r_7</id>

<ab>
4. Of <i>Aurora</i> (as the Poet says)<lb/>
Cephalus told stories to <i>Phocus</i>,<lb/>
How she was seated on Mount <i>Hymettus</i>,<lb/>
Which is perpetually in bloom;<lb/>
Her mouth was red beyond Coral,<lb/>
and that in rising and setting, she always<lb/>
honors the morning and evening,<lb/>
bestowing on them the first and last light.<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Example: how the pain of death was depicted, as well as worry and fear. </ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p029r_8</id>

<ab>
5. Just as <i>Aurora</i> displays her blooming lips<lb/>
early in the morning and late in the evening,<lb/>
at the close of the day as well as its breaking,<lb/>
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Example: how the pain of death was depicted, as well as worry and fear. </ab>

</div>
</root>