<root>
<page>020r</page>

<div>

<id>p020r_1</id>

<ab>
also a sniffing dog, seemingly eager<lb/> 
for something in particular in his pouch<lb/> 
which lay under his head. Yet with such wonder<lb/> 
and joyous eyes the Moon beheld him,<lb/> 
thinking she saw <i>Endymion</i> <lb/> 
</ab>


<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>O<!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>

<div>
<id>p020r_2</id>

<ab>
57. Here too was <i>Paris</i>, who had begun<lb/> 
to carve <i>Oenone</i> in the bark of an elm tree<lb/> 
with a scythe, but was assailed<lb/> 
by three Goddesses and had not been able<lb/> 
to finish completely, but left it thus<lb/> 
in order to offer judgment and prevent conflict<lb/> 
among these three, all standing waiting, naked before him, <lb/> 
who was the most beautiful and worthy of the prize.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin>Here is the main point of the History, that is, the Judgment of Paris.</ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p020r_3</id>

<ab>
58. But what was especially to be observed and respected<lb/> 
as very ingenious, beautiful, and unusual,<lb/> 
was the great attentiveness and unfettered talent<lb/> 
of this judicious painter, through which<lb/> 
there stood, created by him,<lb/> 
<i>Juno</i> and <i>Minerva</i>, both outstandingly lovely,<lb/> 
so completely perfect, that he<lb/> 
could not have done better.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>

<div>
<id>p020r_4</id>

<ab>
59.  Now since he did now know how to make <i>Venus</i> <lb/> 
more beautiful than the other two, which is fitting,<lb/> 
and as these two stood facing forward.<lb/> 
he made the most of this and cleverly painted Venus<lb/> 
with her back turned. Thus the astute Artist <lb/> 
excused himself for delighting with deceit,<lb/> 
suggesting that, if she turned around,<lb/> 
she would surpass the others in beauty. <lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Note here a fine conceit copied from the life of Timanthes: to make observers believe that Venus, if seen from the front, would be the fairest; just as Agamemnon, with head covered, would be deemed the saddest.

</ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p020r_5</id>

<ab>
60.  Many more things, diverse in nature,<lb/> 
were painted here, according to the Poet’s verses.<lb/> 
So these people went to perform their Sacrifice<lb/> 
before the image of <i>Pales</i>, engaging in<lb/> 
much Ceremony, in that building.<lb/> 
But these Examples show us<lb/> 
how to compose with abundance and intelligence,<lb/> 
and thereby happily to Poeticize.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab><margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>
</div>
<div>
<id>p020r_6</id>

<ab>
61. Who, awakened by this, shall not now discover<lb/> 
their wit in Composition by following in the footsteps <lb/> 
of Comedies, where crazy buffoons<lb/> 
or other characters perform<lb/> 
solely to delight the audience:<lb/> 
for [compositions] with so few elements are useless,<lb/> 
performed, they have no perfect<lb/> 
nature, but only additions or supplements.<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in margin --></ab>

</div>
<div>
<id>p020r_7</id>

<ab>
62. Thus one should elaborate a simple History,<lb/> 
like our example of the Poet’s text;<lb/> 
</ab>

<ab>
<margin>right-middle</margin>Sannasarus was a Neapolitan Nobleman who was able to write about painting: how to make additions in a Poetic manner.</ab>

</div>
</root>