<root>
<page>004v</page>

<div>

<id>p004v_1</id>

<ab>
<i>Mars</i> and raging <i>Bellona</i>. This is all excellent evidence.<lb/>

But whoever wants more recent proof need only go (if there is the opportunity), 
to Prague, where there is the greatest lover of painting in the world–that is, the Roman 
<i>Caesar Rudolf</i> the second–in order to see all the magnificent costly pieces in his imperial 
residence and elsewhere, in all the art chambers of the most powerful amateurs. He must 
examine, evaluate, and calculate the value and price of each, to see what considerable 
sum he will find<sup><comment>2 On Rudolf’s collection, see <a href="http://www.habsburger.net/en/chapter/kunst-und-wunderkammer-emperor-rudolf-ii"
 target="_blank">http://www.habsburger.net/en/chapter/kunst-und-wunderkammer-emperor-rudolf-ii</a> See also <a href="http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/rupr/hd_rupr.htm"
 target="_blank">http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/rupr/hd_rupr.htm</a> </comment></sup>.  
 I think that, in his surprise, he will be compelled to admit that our 
painting is a noble, excellent, magnificent and virtuous exercise, which should not yield 
to any other Natural or liberal Art. <lb/>

I myself (for what it is worth) am a Practitioner, a follower of this most laudable 
Art, who hopes that she (however worthy), shall not find me unworthy to set forth her 
foundation, nature, form and being (as much as I can) for her clever, beloved, youthful 
Followers. To this I am willingly inclined, the more so, since I have not seen or heard 
anyone in our own time who has taken in hand this important and agreeable subject for 
the benefit of the Youth who love art. <lb/>

Moreover, I am tempted by a bold desire to follow in this the prominent, great and 
most illustrious <i>Apelles</i>, <i>Antigonus</i>, <i>Xenocrates</i>, and others, our ancient precursors, who 
(as will be heard) have laid open all the mysteries of Art in books and in writing (after 
their knowledge) before the eyes of young Painters. Someone more expert in speech 
could have accomplished this in much finer and more artful language; yet it could be 
feared that, if he himself were not a Painter, he would make frequent errors regarding our 
particulars and our business. <lb/>

This happened in antiquity to <i>Phormio</i>, the Peripatetic philosopher in Ephesus, 
who with powerful eloquence, wished to describe all the virtuous aspects and knowledge 
that an excellent Commander must have; but whose argument <i>Hannibal</i>, the great warrior 
at the time, laughed at because of the great arrogance and ignorance he observed in the 
Man.  <lb/>

Thus, seeing no-one enriched by this desire to write or by diligence, and rather 
than waiting in vain for another, I have over some Years begun setting forth these 
foundations of the art of Painting in rhymed poetry in Flemish, since Young people are 
often drawn to poetry, finding it easier to learn by heart and to remember. <lb/>

At the beginning I did not have a proper understanding of French poetic meter, 
yet I am not pleased by our own old limping style. I say “limping,” because we did not 
use lines of a single meter. Therefore I have followed the Italian <i>ottava</i>, then used our 
own rhyme scheme. I have used no rhymes of one syllable, nor those in which the final 
syllables rhyme, which are called <i>Masculin</i> by the French, and which I call in Flemish, 
“standing rhymes;” but I have everywhere rhymed the penultimate syllable, which I call 
“falling,” and the French call <i>Feminin</i>. I have also avoided rhyming the third from the 
last syllable, which I call “stumbling” after the Italian, in which they are called <i>Druccioli</i>. 
I have avoided using the same rhyme within a hundred lines, though with digressions and 
other things<lb/>
</ab>


<ab><margin>left-middle</margin><!-- Nothing in the margin --></ab>
</div>
</root>